<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vindication of truth, as held forth in a book, entituled, Love to the lost, from the lies, slanders and deceits of T. Higgenson, in a book, called, A testimony to thc [sic] true Iesus. But he is discovered to hold forth another Iesus then what the Scriptures hold forth, or the saints witness. / I.N.</title>
            <author>Naylor, James, 1617?-1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 130 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89857</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N326</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E886_8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202994</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863106</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863106</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115288</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89857)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115288)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 133:E886[8])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vindication of truth, as held forth in a book, entituled, Love to the lost, from the lies, slanders and deceits of T. Higgenson, in a book, called, A testimony to thc [sic] true Iesus. But he is discovered to hold forth another Iesus then what the Scriptures hold forth, or the saints witness. / I.N.</title>
                  <author>Naylor, James, 1617?-1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 56 [i.e. 57], [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert, and are to be sold at the Black-Spread-Eagle at the west end of Pauls.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>I.N. = James Naylor.</note>
                  <note>"Love to the lost" is by Naylor.</note>
                  <note>P. 57 misnumbered 56.</note>
                  <note>Annoation on Thomason copy: "Septemb. 9".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Higgenson, Thomas. --  Testimony to the true Jesus and the faith of him --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Naylor, James, 1617?-1660. --  Love to the lost --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115288:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A VINDICATION OF TRUTH, As held forth in a Book, ENTITULED, LOVE TO THE LOST, From the Lies, Slanders and Deceits of T. HIGGENSON, in a Book, called, <hi>A Testimony to the true Ieſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But he is diſcovered to hold forth another Ieſus then what the Scriptures hold forth, or the Saints witneſs.</p>
            <p>I. N.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> and are to be ſold at the <hi>Black-Spread-Eagle</hi> at the Weſt End of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1656.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115288:2"/>
            <head>A Vindication of Truth, as held forth in a Book, entituled, <hi>Love to the Loſt.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Friend,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou ſayes, thou <hi>ſhall preſent a veiw of that Spirit that is in the Quakers, having ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained a more perfect underſtanding of that way, and ſum of our faith and profeſſion, which,</hi> thou ſayes, <hi>is come forth ſigned by James Naylor:</hi> And this, thou ſayes, thou wilt do in love to us.</p>
            <p>To which I ſay, that which is come forth by <hi>James Nayler,</hi> was preſented already, and hadſt thou been able to have ſaid ſomething againſt it, as by me preſented, and proved it in plainneſs, not to have been the faith and ſpirit that was in the holy men of God, then hadſt thou done ſomething to purpoſe: But in that thou haſt left what truth I preſented, and inſtead thereof haſt preſented a heap of falſhoods and deceits out of thy own boſom, as like my words as thou well could make a lie, to the truth: And haſt made peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple beleive thou haſt diſproved ſomething of mine, when thy work hath but been, to fight with thy own falſhood, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found thy ſelf inſtead of confuting me. This makes it appear, that thou art not perfect in thy underſtanding of our way and ſpirit, the ſum of our faith and profeſſion, or elſe wickedly igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, that thou mayſt take occaſion, to caſt thy reproach upon us and the truth and faith we profeſs. Indeed who reads my book and thy ſlanders gathered from thence (as thou pretends)
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115288:3"/>
will ſay the later is the more like, ſeeing thou haſt ſo often repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted over thy own wicked ſlanders, fathering them on me, which hath no footing at all in my book; As that I deny the perſon of Chriſt, the death of Chriſt, the bloud of Chriſt, the once offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſt for all, &amp;c. that I ſay the light in every man is God, and Chriſt, and Redemption, is the baptiſm of Chriſt, is Gods Righteouſneſs, and many ſuch like abominable lyes, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſpoken by me, which thou often over accuſeſt me that I ſay, ſo that any moderate man may wonder that ever any who have but a ſhew of religion, ſhould be ſo void of the fear of God, or have ſo little bridle for the tongue, as thou haſt ſhewed in this thy work.</p>
            <p>But that conceit thou haſt of being juſtified before thou waſt born, and before either faith or works hath given thee ſuch a diſpenſation, as that thou matters not much what thou ſayeſt; being juſtified beforehand, nought thou doſt can condemn thee; Chriſt hath born away all thy ſins, before thou was begotten or born, and thou ſhalt never bear them, nor they be charged upon thee; a principle of wickedneſs, called faith, to cheat the ſoules of people, and keep them bold in their ſins, at which all that knows the righteouſneſs of God, and his terrors againſt ſin, may weep to think on.</p>
            <p>And in all which, inſtead of diſcovering our ſpirit, thou are diſcovered, thy ſpirit and foundation; but what is come forth ſigned by <hi>James Nayler</hi> ſtands as it was, thy lies being taken away; which ſome of them I ſhall lay open, with thy confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons thereupon, as to the later part of thy book, which pretends an anſwer to my writing in <hi>Love to the loſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other part (though a heap of confuſion) I ſhall not much meddle with as to anſwer, the ſubſtance thereof falling within the other part, nor ſhall I write much to any of it, truth is tryed and ſtands not by words.</p>
            <p>So to the firſt particular as followeth.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Firſt, Concerning the fall of man.</head>
               <p>ANd in this thou tels of the ſum of things ſpoken by me, but ſums up thy own lies amongſt it, not having matter from my words to accuſe me with.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:115288:3"/>
Doth my words ſay, that Gods own Wiſdom and Spirit re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains in faln man, but as a captive? and that that was his fall? or do I ſay, that by looking and turning not to any thing without, but to that of God lying under and covered within him, and that that is the bloud of the Croſs, and his redemption? Art not thou aſhamed, inſtead of anſwering to my words, to become an accuſer openly? had it not been thy wiſdom rather to have been ſilent, if thou durſt not have entred upon my words as they ſtand, then to have made thy ſelf way with lies? and then to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove thy lies thy ſelf? And not any thing that I have ſaid doſt thou appear againſt; onely in thy ſeeming anſwer or miſt which thou caſts, thou adds more lies, ſaying, that I ſay, that there is that in the natural man, which being turned into, and followed, can redeem and make attonement, a thing never ſpoken by me, nor never entred into my heart, for it is in the ſpiritual man that the attonement is made, and not in the natural.</p>
               <p>Thou further ſayes, <hi>That the obedience of Chriſt was not the righteouſneſs of one;</hi> which is as falſe concerning Chriſt, as the other concerning me, as whoever reads <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 18, 19, ſhall read there in plain words.</p>
               <p>Other things thou ſayes, As <hi>that we are not made righteous by looking back and turning to the firſt</hi> Adam, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> A thing never ſpoken by me nor intended, onely thou doſt diſprove thy own deceitful ſlander caſt on my words, and ſo in the moſt places of thy book, which I ſhall not much mention, ſeeing they touch not my words, as he that reads my words may ſee, not one ſentence of mine haſt thou diſproved in this anſwer.</p>
               <p>Thou adds a piece of falſe doctrine, which I ſhall diſcover; Thou ſayes, <hi>by looking out of everything in man to the ſecond</hi> Adam, I ſay, he whoſe eyes is without and not within, cannot ſee the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> for he cannot be ſeen but by revelation, and in ſpirit he is known and ſeen ſince his aſcention, and hath been to all his, as theſe Scriptures will plainly prove, <hi>Galat. 1. 16. Col. 1. 27.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And I demand of thee and all thy generation, to make it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, how the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> is now ſeen, but in the ſpirit by faith within; till then blame me not for ſaying this of thine is falſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115288:4"/>
doctrine. I know there is a ſort of you, who have conceited a carnal ſight, and have run in your carnal expectations from year to year therein, till you are become ſpiritually blind, but if that be it thou here intends, thou muſt reckon thy ſelf for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent amongſt thoſe who have neither ſeen him, nor known him, who denies his revelation in ſpirit; and ſo being intruding in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that which the eye hath not ſeen, no marvel though thou ſpeak ſo darkly of him as thou doſt in this thy book, and would lead men from the ſpirit to ſeek Chriſt the Lord, who is that Spirit, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 17, 18. and would lead without to ſeek him whom none of you can find, but within.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning Light and Life.</head>
               <p>ANd this alſo thou dare not enter on as it ſtands, but that thou may be ſeen to ſay ſomewhat as though thou oppoſed me: Thou makes a lie of thy own, ſaying, that I ſay, <hi>that the light ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in every man is Chriſt;</hi> a thing never written nor intended by me. And when thou haſt ſet up this lie, thou fals in hand to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute it, to make people believe thou was confuting my words, when thou art but declaring in print what deceit hath long been hid in thy own boſome, and that the lyar and deceiver is one in thee, ſo having laid thee open, I have no more to do in that quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel, having denied the lie and its founder, what I have writ ſtands as it was.</p>
               <p>Onely another error I ſhall reprove thee of, that is, thou ſayes, <hi>That all falſe Religions and errors are bottomed upon the law in the Conſcience;</hi> And this is falſe and contrary to Scripture, for the great myſtery of faith, that diſcovers all errors and falſe Religions, is held in the Conſcience, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 9. And the Apoſtles rejoycing was the teſtimony of their Conſcience, and they did not rejoyce in the ground of errors; and by the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer of a good Conſcience the Saints are ſaved by the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Jeſus, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 21. and they are not ſaved by the ground of errors. And the law that is written in the Conſcience is that which God hath written, and the law of the new Covenant of life and light which diſcovers all errors, and which leads to know God, as is plain, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8. 10, 11. And thou that teaches
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115288:4"/>
people, that the Law which God hath written within man is the ground of errors, teacheſt blaſphemy. And this law in ſpirit is that perfect law of liberty, that whoſoever looks unto and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueth therein, he being a doer of the work, that man ſhall be bleſſed in his deed, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1. 25. And by this ſpiritual law of life was the Saints made free from the law of ſin and death; and the righteouſneſs of this law it was that Chriſt fulfilled in the Saints, who walked after the law of the Spirit, and not after the letter of the Law, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 1, 2, 3, 4. And this Righteouſneſs which the Saints beleived and waited for to be fulfilled in them, is that which thou art preaching againſt, and would have all to ſhut it out, and then the devil might dwell ſafe within; and they that did wait for this righteouſneſs of the law fulfilling in them, did not deny the bloud of Chriſt, as thou falſly would ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe us, who witneſs the ſame Righteouſneſs of ſaith within, and not of the letter without, for we know (and ſo did they) that none can have this righteouſneſs of faith fulfilled in them, but who beleives that one offering once for all, and by his blood we have acceſs to that faith; by which is declared that everlaſting Righteouſneſs of God for Juſtification, to which till then we was ſtrangers and could not come, but now have an inheritance therein.</p>
               <p>And as we know, that none can come to have this Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs wrought in them, unleſs they beleive in his bloud and ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſice once offered, ſo alſo we know, That none by taking of what was done at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and ſay, they beleive in it, without this work, can be ſaved, as the Scripture ſaith in plain words, <hi>James</hi> 2. 14. to the end of the chapter, which Scriptures may ſerve to ſhew thy ſpirit, and what nature thy work is of, and thy faith that denies Gods righteouſneſs within, to be meer imagination, and ſuch a faith none of Gods people ever preached or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed.</p>
               <p>Another peice of confuſion I ſhall mind thee on, here in this thou confeſſeth Chriſt to be the ſame word as the Spirit of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation in us, and that ſo he is the light within us: And in thy laſt thou denyed any to look to the glory of the Godhead ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nng forth on man, but they muſt look off from every thing in man; ſo by thy own doctrine, we muſt not look to the glory of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115288:5"/>
the God head ſhining forth on us, nor to the Spirit of revelation, nor to Chriſt the light within us, theſe thou haſt forbidden, and yet thou would make people beleive thou was a Miniſter for God and Chriſt. A blind way haſt thou made for ſuch as will follow thee, who muſt neither look to glory of the Godhead ſhining on them, nor to Chriſt in them, but they that are wiſe may compare thy doctrine with Chriſts and his Apoſtles in theſe Scriptures, <hi>Luke</hi> 17. 21. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 6, 7. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 9, 10, 11, 12, 14. where you may ſee to what the Saints looked, and when it was, and where their hope and faith was, and whether without or within, <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 27. and where their faith and hope was, there was their righteouſneſs, wherein they walked, and to which they became ſervants, and whereby they became free from ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4 but Gods righteouſneſs in man the devil likes not, but to talk on and let him keep poſſeſſion, that likes him well and his ſervants, for he that ſerves Gods Righteouſneſs in his heart, can be no ſervant of ſin, for his ſervants you are to whom you obey, whether of ſin unto death, or of obedience unto righteouſneſs, <hi>Rom</hi> 6. 16. And as out of the heart of the wicked proceeds that which defiles, becauſe of the blindeſs of their hearts, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. So he that keeps his heart with all diligence, from thence are the iſſues of life, <hi>Prov.</hi> 4. 23. and he that hath not righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs in his heart, hath none at all, but where the word of faith is known in the heart, that mans righteouſneſs is not at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, nor his ſalvation to ſeek, for with the heart man beleives unto righteouſneſs; but is not that a blind doctrine, which preaches God and Chriſt within, but that Righteouſneſs that juſtifies not in them? It ſeems thou imagines, that God, when he comes to dwell in man, leaves his Righteouſneſs behind him, or that righteouſneſs, that then is in him, is not able to juſtifie him, but the Saints that knew juſtification, knew the gift of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs for it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. And juſtification by the Spirit, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 11. And everlaſting Righteouſneſs brought in, whereby tranſgreſſion is finiſhed, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. 24. but a generation there is, who <hi>turn judgement into gall, and the fruit of righteouſneſs into bemlock,</hi> Amos 6. 12. <hi>Hearken you ſtout. hearted who are far from righteouſneſs, I will bring neer my righteouſneſs, and it ſhall not be far off, Iſai.</hi> 46. 12, 13. And what I have ſaid may anſwer to the next also.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:115288:5"/>
               <head>Concerning Righteouſneſs.</head>
               <p>ANd in this, like the reſt, thou firſt makes a lie of thy own to confute, but my words thou canſt not enter, Thou ſayes, the ſum of our faith is, <hi>that the imputed Righteouſneſs that juſtifies is the I ght within;</hi> a thing by me never ſpoken or written. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, thou ſayes, That <hi>nothing is ſaid by me of Chriſt manifeſt in fleſh, or his crucified body, or righteouſneſs that way:</hi> Poor man, how hath wickedneſs over-run thee to add lie to lie? Are not theſe my words, <hi>That Righteouſneſs that God accepteth is but one, which is his own, perfectly fulſilled and manifeſt in the world in Jeſus Chriſt, the Light and Savi ur thereof, and that none inherits it ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than they receive the Son of righteouſneſs:</hi> And is this nothing of Chriſt? but it is no new thing to me, to ſee the refuge of lies, with that ſpirit which now oppoſeth; nor for me to be called a Railer, becauſe I will not either ſay they are truths, or find out ſome finer name to call them than lies. But to leave them and go on to thy doctrine: thou ſayes, <hi>We are juſtified without works onely through faith;</hi> which is as falſe as the Scripture is true, for faith the Apoſtle, <hi>Ye ſee then how that by works a man is juſtified, and not by faith onely, James</hi> 2. 24. And Chriſt faith, <hi>By thy words thou ſhalt be justified, and by thy words thou ſhalt be condemned,</hi> Math. 12. 37. <hi>And not the hearers of the Law, but the doers are juſt before God, Rom.</hi> 2. 13. Now if theſe Scriptures be true; then thine is falſe, but ſuch is thy blindneſs, that becauſe the Scriptures doth exclude the works of the Law for juſtification, therefore thou wilt exclude the works of faith which are wrought in God alſo. A fine eaſie way to ſalvation, and well pleaſing to you that love your luſts, but that neither God nor Scripture knows it, nor the Saints practiſe.</p>
               <p>Further thou ſayes, <hi>He that can but beleive this is perfectly pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and there is no more conſcience of ſin, though yet the feeling of ſin:</hi> I ſay, what is thou now intends? feeling of ſin but make no conſcience: Is not this plain Ranting, to commit ſin and feel it, and make no conſcience of it, this indeed is the ready way to murther the Witneſs, to ſtop the ear at his reproof, and to make ſhipwrack of a tender conſcience, and ſo in time to get it ſeared,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115288:6"/>
and ſo no more conſcience of ſin, do what you will do, but ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine all is pardoned, paſt, preſent and to come, let the light in the conſcience ſay what it can, hope againſt hope, ſayeſt thou, <hi>The Righteouſneſs of Chriſt is a covering upon ſin, &amp;c.</hi> I ſay, I know who repents and turns to him he doth. But doth Chriſts Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs cover ſin to come, and whilſt men are committing it? one day thou wilt find, that it is not covered, but thou that haſt ſeared thy conſcience, it will appear when thou ſhalt ceaſe to deal treacherouſly with the witneſs that would have dealt truly with thee, but how is Chriſts Righteouſneſs a covering on thy ſin, when thy ſin is in thy heart, and thy cover no nearer than above the Stars: If ever God look down upon the earth thou wilt be found naked, and the day is upon thee, look to it, thy Ranting faith hath not long to laſt, and thy cover will be but deceit, wo to thee that art covered, and not with the Spirit.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the word.</head>
               <p>IN this, like the reſt, thou enters with a lie, ſaying, <hi>That we ſay the light within all men is the word,</hi> not minding at all to ſpeak truth; thou tels of ſin being covered, but the liar is openly ſeen, and ſhames not: And when thou haſt made one lie, thou infers another from it, <hi>If the Light within every man be the Word, then all ages have had the Goſpel in equality, &amp;c.</hi> Then thou adds ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as falſe as the reſt, ſaying, <hi>That Truth ſayes, the Light is the remaining ſparkles of the Law, and repreſents God onely under a vail;</hi> When Truth ſaith, the Life is the Light of men, and this is that true <hi>Light that lighteth every man that comes into the world, John</hi> 1. And Chriſt ſaith, <hi>I am the Light of the world, he that follows me ſhall not abide in darkneſs, but ſhall have the light of life, John</hi> 8. 12. And the Saints came to the knowledge of God in the face of Jeſus, by the light within, and this was not onely un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the vail which was in the face of Jeſus, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 6. though vailed to thee, who denies the light of the Spirit, and ſayeth, <hi>truth ſayes it,</hi> when truth denies thee therein, nor haſt thou one Scripture that ſaith ſo.</p>
               <p>And when thou haſt ſhewed thy Spirit by thy works, then thou art forced to confeſs him to be within his in ſpirit the word
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115288:6"/>
of revelation, yet would make two words, a word of Reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation, and a word of Revelation, and in dividing this word in. to two, thou confounds thy ſelf:</p>
               <p>Firſt, thou ſayes, <hi>theſe two are not one without the other:</hi> then thou ſayes, <hi>the one muſt finiſh his work before the other could come;</hi> and ſuch blind muddy ſtuffe thou art bewing in, but what I write in my book ſtands as it was.</p>
               <p>Yet thou adds two lies more; the firſt is, <hi>That we beleive not the word of Reconciliation,</hi> which thou cals thy firſt word, which is falſe, for though we beleive not two words, yet we beleive that one word, which is the word of Reconciliation and Revelation, and there is not another: Thy ſecond lie is of the Light, in ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, it knows Chriſt in neither.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning worſhip.</head>
               <p>IN this thou ſayes, that I affirm, <hi>that the Spirit of Life from God, wherein is the mind, will and love of God, the name, power and wiſdom of Chriſt, wherewith alone God can be acceptably worſhipped, is in every man:</hi> A thing that never entred into my heart, but ſurely friend, thou matters not what thou ſayes, thus to add thy wickedneſs and falſe accuſations, becauſe I ſay none muſt follow the traditions of others, but as every creature is moved by the preſence of the living God; do I therefore ſay, that the ſpirit of God is in every man, this concluſion is more wickedneſs than weakneſs. But to thy doctrine.</p>
               <p>Thou ſayes, <hi>The word of faith ſayes, that the Law without, or Spirit in every man, that ſayes, do this and live, are the vail, &amp;c.</hi> I ſay, where doth the word of faith ſay, that the Spirit within is a vail? or where doth it call the Spirit within the Law without? thou muſt find a new word for this, for the true everlaſting Word ſaith not ſo, but faith, <hi>There is a ſpirit in man, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration of the Almighty giveth them underſtanding, Job.</hi> 32. 8. but doth, not ſay, that that Spirit of God is the vail of which Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit I am ſpeaking, whatever thou pervert it to; but is all thy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual teaching come to this, that the Spirit, in which God will be worſhipped, becomes a vail, and that to abide in any law or light whatſoever, either from within or without, and to be exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115288:7"/>
therein, as to be redeemed or perfected thereby, this, they ſay, is to worſhip God as in the fleſh; haſt thou not here whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly excluded the light of Chriſt, as to be exerciſed therein for freedom and perfection? before thou did but deny it Within, but now thou haſt denied all light whatſoever, both from within and without, for bringing to freedom or perfection, ſo that henceforth all that will own thy doctrine, muſt beleive to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected in the dark, for all light whatſoever thou haſt excluded, ſo that a Chriſt without light muſt now be beleived by all that own thy faith or doctrine, and indeed it ſuits well with thy pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, witneſs thy many lie, in thy book, which are not works of the day.</p>
               <p>Further thou ſayes, <hi>That the light within every man is not the way to the Spirit of Chriſt;</hi> which I need not think ſtrange, ſeeing thou haſt denied all light.</p>
               <p>Alſo thou ſayeſt, <hi>That the works of the Law and the waiting of the Light within, are all one,</hi> if any man will beleive thy blind te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony.</p>
               <p>Thou ſayeſt, <hi>That principle may lead to a ſpirit of activity for God, in the contemplations of him, as a pure and holy God, but it is a far other principle, that is, Chriſt crucified for us, and the faith of him that leads unto that Spirit of peace:</hi> And ſo by thy doctrine there are two principles that leads to God, the one far off the other. But muſt we beleive this becauſe thou ſayeſt it? when not one of the holy men of God thou canſt inſtance, who ever ſaid, that that Spirit that led to contemplations of the pure God, was a far other principle than that of Chriſt that leads to peace: Chriſt ſaith, <hi>No man knoweth the Father, but he to whom the Son reveals him, Math.</hi> 11. 27. But thou ſayes, <hi>Its a far other principle that brings to contemplations of a pure God:</hi> That blind ſpirit of thine clearly ſhowes, what thou knows of contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions with God, who denies the principle of Chriſt to lead there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, but it is like the reſt of thy blind ſtuffe, who would make peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple beleive, that the light of Chriſt leads to blot out the the heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the perſon of Chriſt, ſurely a blinder peice of work hath not been ſeen, but it muſt needs be ſo with thee, who hath denied all light, and art fighting againſt it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:115288:7"/>
               <head>Concerning error, hereſie, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>HEre thou tels us thy former lie over again, ſaying, that I ſay, <hi>That the light within every man is the ſpirit of truth:</hi> and then thou tels how thou haſt diſproved it before: and ſo flaidly fals into another diſcourſe, not at all to the purpoſe as to my words yet adds another lie, ſaying, <hi>That we beleive in God, as by the light in men, redeeming from ſin; but not as in the man Jeſus, having done it already:</hi> and that <hi>we deny the witneſs of the Son;</hi> and that <hi>we have neither Son nor Father;</hi> which is but thy three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold cord of wickedneſs: Thou adds another in thy concluſion, and ſayes, <hi>It is not an errour to divide from the light within;</hi> ſo by thy doctrine, we may divide from the ſpiritual light of Chriſt and not erre; but how ſhouldeſt thou count it an error to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide from the light within, who haſt excluded all manner of light within, and without alſo whatever, to be exerciſed in as the way to perfection: If it be not an error to divide from the light, then it muſt be an error to divide from the darkneſs, for there is but theſe two, and the one muſt needs be an error: But it is eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeen whoſe word thou drives; who art ſet to oppoſe the light, ſuch a work as none of Gods was ever found in, wert thou not blind thou might ſuſpect thy ſelf, who cannot produce one of thy faith in the Scripture.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning Faith.</head>
               <p>IN this accuſation alſo is two lies, firſt, that I ſay, <hi>that the light in every man is Gods righteouſneſs, perfection.</hi> Secondly, thou ſayes, <hi>I ſay not a word of the faith in the perſon of Chriſt, or the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of God in him for us:</hi> The firſt never ſpoken of by me. To the ſecond, my words are theſe, That the living faith is in Chriſt Jeſus, and that true faith layes hold on Gods Righteouſneſs, and by it comes to be created in Chriſt Jeſus unto good works, Gods workmanſhip. Is this not a word of the perſon of Chriſt, nor the operation of God in him? Can one own Chriſt Jeſus, and deny faith in the perſon of Chriſt? Or can one witneſs Gods workmanſhip in him, and not one word of the operation of God
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115288:8"/>
in him? Oh ſhameleſs man, how doeſt thou bend thy tongue for lies and ſlanders.</p>
               <p>Further thou ſayeſt, <hi>that the ſcope of our doctrine, in the height and depth of it ſeems plainly this, that a meaſure of the eternal divinity is in every man, by turning where unto out of all ſayings, operations, Scriptures, or Chriſt without, the ſame doth purge away ſin and redeems unto God.</hi> All which is no more but thine own wickedneſs heaped up, from thy foregoing lies.</p>
               <p>Then thou comeſt to thy doctrine: And that is, to look away from all voice; of conſcience within, and from all things in the heart, whether good or evil, and to look to Jeſus with out though we be in bondage: and this, thou ſayes, <hi>is to receive the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of Chriſt by faith:</hi> But where doeſt thou receive this righteouſneſs, or with what is it ſeen, or what effect hath it, ſeeing thou haſt denied all voices in the conſcience, all things in the heart, and conclude the creature in bondage? they are blind indeed who cannot ſee this righteouſneſs of thine thou lookeſt too (without any thing in the heart or conſcience) to be but meer imagination, a talk of righteouſneſs which thou haſt not in thee.</p>
               <p>And in thy next, having forgot thy doctrine, ſayes, <hi>That by him all that beleive are juſtified from all things, by the Law of the Spirit, according to the Conſcience from which they could not be justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the Law of Moſes:</hi> And alſo ſaves, <hi>That the anſwer of a good Conſcience in the reſurrection of Jeſus, will be found to be that which ſaves before God, and brings forth the true glory within.</hi> What confuſion is here? Muſt all voices of the conſcience be denied, and yet juſtified by the Law of the Spirit, according to the Conſcience, and ſaved by the anſwer of a good Conſcience? and muſt we be juſtified by the law of the Spirit, and the works of the Law written within be denied, and called the fleſh? and muſt we be ſet free and juſtified from all theſe things, by the Law of the Spirit, and the anſwer of a good Conſcience, and yet in bondage? And after thou haſt ſaid, <hi>We must be justified by the Law of the Spirit, according to the Conſcience, and ſaved by a good Conſcience;</hi> then thou confutes that again, and ſaith, <hi>The Law in the Conſcience, which is holy, just and pure, is the ſame with the Covenant of works;</hi> and ſayes, <hi>how holy and pure ſoever it be, it
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115288:8"/>
ſhall not preſerve blameleſs.</hi> Was there ever ſuch a heap of confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and contradictions gathered together? Are theſe thy bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, with which thou art weighing us, which thou tels of? Or is this a ſtanding meaſure, which ſtaggereth to and fro like a drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken man, contradicting and confounding thy ſelf? till there be not a word thou ſayes will ſtand, which is unconfounded from thy own mouth: Is not here <hi>Babels</hi> foundation diſcovered to the weakeſt eye opened in any heart? But this is brought to paſs by the Lord, for the Nations muſt not long be deceived with your witchcrafts, whoredoms, he is laying open to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, with what you have fed them, and where with all you have covered them, and how you have made them to truſt in confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and brought forth a lie for their ſalvation, wherein you have made them to rejoyce over the ſlain, and to truſt in emptineſs, putting the Lord afar off, and caſting the Law of his Covenant behind your backs: but now your skirts is laying open, and your filthineſs appears, your hearts void of righteouſneſs, your tongues muſt needs utter confuſion.</p>
               <p>One thing more of thy falſe doctrine, before I paſs from this particular, and that is, <hi>That men are juſtified and ſin waſhed away before either faith or works;</hi> and this thou affirms in plain words, which is a ſtrange doctrine, and indeed a doctrine of devils, which denies the faith, and ſets up an imagination in its ſtead; for if we be juſtified; and ſin waſhed away, before either faith or works, then are we not juſtified by faith; for we cannot be ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by that which is not: And if this doctrine be true, that men are juſtified before either faith or work, then is not faith of abſolute neceſſity, a man may be ſaved without it, for he that is juſtified and his ſin waſhed away, cannot be damned: he that will beleive this doctrine of thine, need not matter much what he do, this faith is that with which you lead people without faith of God to make no conſcience of ſin, but beleive that they are purged, though they feel themſelves ſervants of ſin, and in bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage thereto.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning Hope.</head>
               <p>ANd the thing thou charges me with in this is, <hi>That I ſay, to hope that that of God in every man, or a Chriſt, may be revealed
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115288:9"/>
to take away ſin, to give freedom from ſin in this life, is the pure, the reaſonable hope, that makes not aſhamed.</hi> In this thou haſt mixed a truth and a lie together; and they muſt be ſevered, that the truth may be owned, and the lie returned to the founder, <hi>That of God in every man can take away ſin,</hi> that is thine own, take it again; but <hi>that Chriſt may be revealed in this to take away ſin,</hi> that hope I own, and am not aſhamed thereof, which thou ſeems to oppoſe.</p>
               <p>Another charge thou layes upon me is, that I ſay, <hi>To hope ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, while the Witneſs in the conſcience condemns of ſin, is the Devils hope:</hi> Which accuſation is utterly falſe, and the words not ſo ſpoken by me, for I own a hope before the Conſcience be wholly purified, which hope leads to the purifying, and that is holden forth by me ſeveral times, and therefore am far off from calling that the devils hope. But my words are theſe, But the Devil hath begot another hope, as like this as may be in his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, which ſtands in another ground, and brings forth another fruit, and that is, though they be ſervants of ſin yet there is hopes of ſalvation, and ſuch hopes as may not be judged nor queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, although the witneſe of God in the Conſcience doth te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie the contrary; yet it muſt not be heeded, leaſt they be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded; ſo where the Devil is become a teacher, a tender Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience muſt be reſiſted; and ſuch a hope ſet up as holds, that to hope in Chriſt within, is to deny the preſence of Chriſt, &amp;c. and many ſuch expreſſions there is, which clearly ſhews how thou haſt perverted my words, contrary to all reaſon and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty to ſlander withal, that becauſe I condemn that hope to be of the Devil, which hopes not freedom from ſin, as well as free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom from hell, that therefore I condemn him that hopes for ſalvation, while yet the Conſcience is not wholly purged.</p>
               <p>But to come to thy doctrine, thou ſayeſt, <hi>To reſt in hope that thou art ſaved already from ſin and wrath in Chriſt the Head, whileſt Conſcience condemns thee of ſin, this is the hope of faith a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the hope of the Law and Conſcience.</hi> I ſay, to hope for free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom from ſin, whileſt yet the Conſcience condemns for ſin, this hope I own, which is not againſt the Conſcience, but leads to a pure Conſcience. But thou that hopes, that thou art already ſaved from ſin and wrath, whileſt thou art a ſervant of ſin, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115288:9"/>
the wrath of God appears to condemn thee for ſin in thy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, thou art he that hopes in a lie, for he that is the ſervant of ſin is not already freed from ſin; thou may well ſay this hope is againſt the Conſcience, and againſt the Law of God alſo, ſuch a hope as none of the Children of God never hoped in, whoſe rejoycing was the teſtimony of their Conſcience, and their hope was according to a good Conſcience, but never hoped againſt their Conſcience, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 12.</p>
               <p>Diddeſt thou not in thy laſt ſay, That men muſt be juſtified by the law of the Spirit according to conſcience, and ſaved by the anſwer of a good Conſcience? And doeſt thou now tell them, That the hope of grace and faith is againſt Law and Conſcience, or ſenſe and feeling: Is not this to make the law void by that which thou cals grace? and to makeſh pwrack of a pure Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and ſo become paſt feeling? like thoſe thou may read on, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 18, 19.</p>
               <p>Further thou goes on, and ſayes, <hi>That hope that is begotten not by the letter, but by the inhabiting or abiding Spirit, there it is a hope beholding the glory of the Lord, and changing the creature into his Image, that hope ſees the love of the Father ſhed forth upon us in the bloud of Atonement, &amp;c.</hi> But how apt art thou to forget thy ſelf! Diddeſt thou not in thy laſt forewarn all for looking to any thing, whether good or evil, in the heart and conſcience within? And is it now by that inhabiting and abiding Spirit, that reveals the blood of Atonement and finiſhes all ſin? So by thy doctrine, it is within in the inhabiting and abiding Spirit that ſees the bloud of Attonement, but thou haſt fore warned all not to look at it, nor at any thing within, good or evil. And yet ſayes, <hi>We are ſaved through faith according to the inward man;</hi> and much ſuch like confuſed ſtuffe, which is wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſs to repeat after thee, were it not for the ſeeds ſake, that they may be led out of thy deceit.</p>
               <p>Is not this a ſtrange doctrine, to ſay, that we are ſaved through faith, according to the inward man, and yet muſt not look to any thing in the heart or conſcience (be it good or bad?) Is not that like to be a blind ſalvation, which is within and muſt not be looked at? But it ſeems thou haſt followed thy doctrine in thy practiſe, for hadeſt thou looked to any thing of God in thy
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115288:10"/>
heart, or to the anſwer of a good Conſcience, it would have put a ſtop to the numberleſs number of thy lies and confuſion in thy book; but a large liberty the Devil hath, when nothing muſt be looked too in the heart or conſcience (either good or bad) to beleive in or follow for ſalvation out of ſin, and yet thou ſayes, <hi>We muſt be ſaved according to the inward man,</hi> which inward man muſt onely be for you to talk on, but muſt not be looked at.</p>
               <p>Thou further ſayes, <hi>That to know Chriſt onely as within (is an error:)</hi> Yet doth not ſhew how a man might know him, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than he is revealed within, nor is he known, as he ought to be, ſince his Aſcention any other way, but onely as he revealeth himſelf in Spirit within, onely you imagine you know him, who never ſaw him, heard him, felt him, or underſtood him, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than by his Spirit within; and what a knowledge that is, which is void of all theſe, is eaſily ſeen to them where he is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed, though hear-ſay Teachers with their litteral knowledge was ever blind.</p>
               <p>But ſeeing thou ſayeſt, <hi>It is an error to know him onely within:</hi> What ſayeſt thou of the A poſtle doctrine, who exhorts to know Chriſt no more after the fleſh, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 16? Muſt not their knowledge then be onely after the Spirit, which muſt be no more after the fleſh? But however he be known, thou haſt denied him, if he be light, either within or without; who ſayes, <hi>To abide in any light what ſoever, either from within or without, and to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed therein as to be perfected thereby, or redeemed from ſin, is to worſhip God in the fleſh.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning Love.</head>
               <p>ANd thy Charge in this is, that I ſay, <hi>It is the love of God to the world, whereby he hath given every man a light, to condemn ſin in the fleſh, and take it away through walking after the Spirit, and that this love of God in the creature doth not flatter ſin in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Charge is not altogether ſo falſe as the reſt, though not wholly true: For I do not ſay, That the light in every man is Gods Son, though I own it to be the light of the Son, that light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115288:10"/>
every man that comes into the world; therefore my words are, That God ſo loved the world, that he gave his Son into the world a light to condemn ſin in the fleſh, that the righteouſneſs of God might be fulfilled in the creature, and my witneſs for this is Chriſt and his Apoſtles, <hi>John</hi> 3 16. to the 22. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 1, 2, 3, 4 and this thou ſeems to oppoſe, but dare not plainly deny it, onely thou haſt power over that of the Charge as far as thy own lie reacheth and no further: And to that, thou ſayes, <hi>was this great and abounding love in ſending his Son, no more but God giving a light in all men,</hi> as though I had ſaid ſo, which is but thine own deceit, to ſet up a lie of thy own to fight with: But I ſay, Gods great love is more than the light, for he hath given his Son, who is not onely that light, but to all that beleive therein and follow it, he leads them out of darkneſs thereby, and gives them the light of life. <hi>John</hi> 8. 12. who doth not onely condemn ſin in the fleſh, but fulfils the righteouſneſs of the Law, in them who walk after the Spirit, and this is my reſtimony of the love of God, which was Chriſts teſtimony and his A poſtles, and ſo thy lie be upon thy own head; and what I have written ſtands ſtill unſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; onely thou mutters that any body ſhould be told of their ſin; and would have us tell people their ſins are forgiven, and that they are juſtified and ſaved, and that Chriſt is come down in your fleſh, and therein hath quenched anger, enmity, ſin and death, with all things that may ſeparate from God: And this we may tell to ſuch as thee, who openly denies Chriſt in thy fleſh, yea, and in all other, row to do any ſuch thing for ſalvation from ſin; ſo how can we ſay that Chriſt is come in your fleſh, and therein through death hath done all this (and not lie?) eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſeeing that you do not onely deny him within you in words, but alſo ſee the anger, enmity, ſin and death unquenched, which hath ſo far ſeparated thee from God, that thou denies God, Chriſt and his Righteouſneſs, and all that may be called light in thee, for ſalvation; ſhould not we be abominable liars, like thee, if we ſhould ſay Chriſt had done all this in thy fleſh, thou thy ſelf would prove us liars, who denies it both in word and practiſe,</p>
               <p>And when thou haſt thus been teaching us to cry peace, even whileſt ſin is in them, to confound thy ſelf in this as in the reſt,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115288:11"/>
thou ſayeſt, <hi>There is a generation that flatters and ſpares in ſin them whom the Lord condemns, this,</hi> thou ſayes, <hi>is to juſtifie the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed:</hi> To which I ſay, were thou not heart blind, and ſo knows not what thou ſpeaks, thou would never ſet us on crying peace, where God cries wo, in the Conſcience for living in ſin, leaſt we juſtifie the wicked, and be guilty of that abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thoutels of.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning Judgement.</head>
               <p>THy Charge in this is, <hi>That my words ſummoned up are, that the light in every man condemning ſin is the miniſtration of judgement and condemnation and as it is received is ſalvation and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption from all uncleanneſs, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To which I anſwer: Deceit hath ſummed them up, and hath thruſt in it ſelf amongſt them as in the reſt: Have I ſaid, <hi>That the light in every man is ſalvation and redemption?</hi> Let them that reads what I have ſaid, judge of thy dealing herein; for my words are, That true judgement, as it is known to men, is a gift from the Spirit of God, ſet in the heart of every one that dwels in the light of Chriſt, and this is far from thy ſayings, who would make people beleive, that I ſay, That the light, as it is in every man, is ſalvation and redemption; for there be many that will not be led to the Redeemer therewith, nor to the Spirit of judgment, but deny all light within and without as thou doeſt, and to theſe it is condemnation, and not ſalvation: but to all that own the Spirit of judgment, which paſſeth upon that which is contrary to the Life of God, ſuch come to be redeemed with judgment, and to ſuch as abide therein doth light and ſalvation ſpring up, to the redeeming the heart from all uncleanneſs; as I have writ in my Book, which thou canſt not contradict.</p>
               <p>And in thy doctrine thou ſayeſt, <hi>That as Chriſt in every age hath come forth more or leſs, ſo in this age he will come forth in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs and ſalvation, and that he will judge the works of the Law, as well as the luſts of the fleſh, and that the ſpirit of Chriſt in his people ſhall judge both Angels and mens ſpiritual and fleſhly wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:115288:11"/>
To which I ſay, Some of this is truth, and we ſhall try the reſt.</p>
               <p>Firſt, What work of the Law is it that God will judge? doeſt thou intend that law, by which, thou confeſſed before, all that believe are juſtified, from that, from which they could not be juſtified by the Law of <hi>Moſes?</hi> If thou intend that Law, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thy doctrine, for the works of that Law of the Spirit of life, by which we are juſtified, are the works of Chriſt, where with he fulfils the Law in his Saints, and ſo are works of the Spirit, and ſhall never come into judgement; and if thou mean not that Law, to me it matters not, I ſhall not contend with thee about a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other of thy imaginations.</p>
               <p>And whereas thou tels of Chriſts coming forth in this age in righteouſneſs and ſalvation, and to judge, and that it is the Spirit of Chriſt in his People that muſt be the Judge both of Angels and men in this his appearance: Haſt not thou in the reſt of thy Book, as much as in thee lies, done what thou canſt to oppoſe this his appearance, who haſt all along denied any thing within to be looked unto for righteouſneſs, ſalvation and judgement? yea, and ere thou get out of the ſame thing, thou art contradicting it again, and ſayes, <hi>Law or form, or light within are the principles of judgment with most:</hi> But ſayeſt thou, <hi>It is a ſmall thing for the ſpiritual man to be judged by any of theſe:</hi> What confuſion is this of thine thou bringeſt forth in oppoſition to the light: Muſt the Spirit of Chriſt in his people judge both Angels and men ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and fleſhly? and yet thou ſpeaks ſcornfully of the light within, and thruſts it in with law and form to make it odious: It ſeems thou canſt not endure, that the Spirit of Chriſt ſhould be called light in his people, it muſt be darkneſs there (it ſeems) or elſe not owned by thee.</p>
               <p>Another lie thoutels of <hi>John,</hi> ſaying, <hi>That he did not call to the light within every man;</hi> and ſayeſt, <hi>no Prophet ſpake of him by the light, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But it ſeems thou haſt not much read the Prophets, or elſe art wickedly ignorant, for all that read them may find them prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſying of a Covenant of light, and <hi>John</hi> ſaith, who ſaw him, <hi>this is the true light that lighteth every man that cometh into the world.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:115288:12"/>
               <head>Concerning Perfection.</head>
               <p>ANd after thy uſual manner, thy firſt work is a lie, ſaying, <hi>That my principal matter is, that perfection is that gift or light in every man:</hi> Another lie is, that I ſay, <hi>Imperfection came in by the miniſtry of Antichriſt:</hi> When the matter of my words are, That God and Chriſt is perfection; and doth not ſay, the gift is perfection, yet I own that every gift of God is perfect, yet God himſelf the perfection of all: I alſo ſay, that imperfection came in by the Devil, and maintained by his Miniſters, who uſes all means to ſupplant truth where it is, and to keep up imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in the world: And thy lies being taken away, the truth ſtands untouched, though many words thou uſeſt, yet dare not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny what I have written in the leaſt particular.</p>
               <p>Onely thou asks ſome queſtions, which thou haſt raiſed out of thy own brain, not at all what I ſay,</p>
               <p>Thy Queſtions are, firſt, <hi>Was Chriſt in the fleſh no more than a Preacher or example of perfection?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. <hi>Was that fulneſs of the Godhead in him, no more than ſuch a light as God hath ſet up in every man?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>3. <hi>Or was his bearing of our ſins, and the wounds for our iniquities, no more but to ſhew how we ſhould bear them in our ſelves?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſay, Yes: He was more than all theſe three, for he in himſelf alone wrought redemption, broke through all difficulties, open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the way of life for all Creatures, became a Sacrifice acceptable to the Father, and triumphed openly over death, the grave and hell, and much more that may be ſpoken of him, which he did in his own perſon, and not onely ſo, but is now an everlaſting of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, from generation to generation, an everlaſting light preached in every Creature, whereby they may receive the faith, (which without it they cannot) whereby to ſee him in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, appearing from heaven in Spirit, as Leader and Teacher, Judge and Law-giver, and in his light to lead, and his life to ſtrengthen, all that beleive in the ſame way, wherein he walked in his own perſon, who left an example, when he aſcended, for all to follow, which will be ſaved, which none can follow nor be
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115288:12"/>
ſaved, but who are led by his light and quickened by his Spirit within them, though they talk never ſo much of him at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> without them: And this is that which the Devil is an enemy to, to wit, that Chriſt ſhould be owned in the hearts of any, as Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Teacher, King and Law-giver, and with his light to enligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten every dark part thereof, ſo that every motion of God is ſeen and received, and every motion of the Devil is ſeen and reſiſted even unto blood, here is little hope for the Devils Kingdom: where this light is received and followed, there the ſoul is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed from the deeds of the devils darkneſs, therefore he ſets on work all his inſtruments, wherein he hath any intereſt, to cry out againſt this light within, for if this light ſhine in the heart, then his ſeat muſt be diſcovered, and the knowledge of God ſeen in the face of Jeſus; and as any come to know God in the light, they will be led out of his ſervice; ſo you ſtand up from all Quarters, who wear his dark livory, crying out againſt the light of Chriſt within, charging all not to hearken to any voice with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, nor mind any thing there good nor bad, that he may keep that place for his kingdom: And to him you are faithful to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt of your power, who are all gathered together in this day of battel to fight againſt the Light, of which thou art not the leaſt, who cryeſt out againſt all light whatſoever, either from within or without, for any to be exerciſed in for freedom from ſin.</p>
               <p>But are you not blind above all that ever was before you, who have ſo many Scriptures declaring the Lambs war againſt all ſorts of Spirits, yet never find them warring againſt the Spirit of light, but with that Spirit of light in them did they make warr againſt the Prince of darkneſs, and all his dark principles in his children. Fooliſh men, how long will it be before you look at your feet, and what way you are going, and try your ſelves whoſe meſſage you carry, who are preaching that which none of you have ſeen for ſalvation: The Saints meſſage was the light both for fellowſhip, and to lead to the bloud of cleanſing, <hi>John</hi> 1. 6, 7. But thy meſſage is not any thing which is called light whatſoever, either from within or without for redemption; and here thou art ſeen to be he that preaches another Goſpel. They preached the Goſpel of light, and thy Goſpel is no light whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115288:13"/>
ſo thou art accurſed and they that follow thee in that faith, which denieth all light whatſoever.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning Obedience.</head>
               <p>IN this thou makes divers things of thine own, never ſpoken nor thought by me; thou ſayes, <hi>They are the ſum of things ſpoken by me;</hi> which indeed are but the foam of thy ſlanderous ſpirit.</p>
               <p>As firſt, <hi>As to be guided in obedience to the ſpirit or light within us, as Chriſt was by the Spirit of the Father in him, that is the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of Chriſt, that the Father cals for the ſame obedience of the beleiver as of Christ, and that,</hi> I ſay, <hi>we are perfectly juſtified by Chriſts obedience when we perform obedience in the ſame meaſure he did:</hi> And divers other untruths haſt thou forged, thereby to ſlander the truth, as though I held forth two obediences, as one of Chriſts, and another of the Creatures: And that the Creature muſt come up as high in his obedience as Chriſt did in his, and ſuch like wicked ſtuffe thou utters, as one having ſold thy ſelf thereto, bending thy tongue like a bow for lies, to ſhoot at the truth in ſecret, but thy arrows muſt peirce thy own bowels, and the Archer into the wilderneſs muſt be driven; but the truth ſhall ſtand for ever. And all that reads what I have written may ſee, that I have denied all ſorts of obedience from Scriptures or others, wrought by man, or in mans will, and owns onely that everlaſting obedience that is in Chriſt, to which every one muſt give up themſelves, as is oftentimes repeated by me: That <hi>it is no more we that live, but Chriſt that liveth in us;</hi> and no further than we partake of his obedience in us, are we accepted with the Father, as Obedient children, which might have ſtopt the mouth of the Liar, hadſt thou not done it wickedly.</p>
               <p>And when thou haſt done, thou pretendeſt to reprove thy lying ſlanders with the ſame ſpirit of ſlander, giving out filthy words of thine own, as though I had lifted up my ſelf equal with the Perſon of Chriſt, to perſorm the ſame obedience for the purging away of ſin, &amp;c. Oh thou full of all ſubtilty and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, where did I ever ſet up my ſelf equal with Chriſt? or ever ſet up any obedience of mine diſtinct from his, or ever ſpoke
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:115288:13"/>
of ſelf obedience for the purging away of ſin? canſt thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold this thy wickedneſs and not be aſhamed? or didſt thou think ever to account for thy words, thy heart could not but tremble at this wickedneſs; but the devil having ſet up an opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in thee of being juſtified without faith, or repentance for all thy ſins paſt, preſent and to come; like the Pope, hath given thee a diſpenſation to wickedneſs, ſo that there is now no ſtop to thy tongue, whatſoever he moves thee to ſay, for to advance his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of darkneſs, thou art ready at his command.</p>
               <p>Thou ſayes, <hi>Thou art one of the leaſt in thy Fathers houſe:</hi> But it ſeems by thy language thou haſt been an apt Scholler, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry diligent in his ſervice, and thou muſt look for thy wages, when thy work thou haſt finiſhed.</p>
               <p>Thou cals them <hi>Pagans,</hi> who deſign not to know another way to divine glory than Chriſt did, and ſayes, <hi>That way is but the depth of Satan.</hi> Oh thou blaſphemer! Is it the depth of Satan to follow Chriſt in his way, and not to deſign another? Sure the other way thou haſt deſigned is lying and deceit, for that way I find thee in; but the Way Chriſt Jeſus I own, and ſo far as I am led therein by the ſame power, ſo I walk; and it is not I but Chriſt in me, who is the Way and the Life, whoſe way is not without a Mediator, as thou would make it, to cover thy blaſphemy for calling it a depth of Sathan, for if that way he walked in was without a Mediator, then was there a time when he was not a Mediator.</p>
               <p>Thou asks me, If I <hi>have not the fulneſs of the Godhead in my ſelf?</hi> I ſay, In ſelf it is not, but of Chriſt I receive of the ſame fulneſs. And many other Queſtions thou asks, which are all in him, wherein is my treaſure, walking in the ſame way, who is the myſtery to be beleived, and example to be followed, which is not two things, as thou falſly ſayes, but one.</p>
               <p>Thou ſayes, <hi>He put an end to the enmity and all evils in himſelf:</hi> I ſay, That is true, but he hath not put an end to it in thee, there it lives and reigns, as thy lying and confuſion may witneſs.</p>
               <p>Thou ſayes, <hi>As thou art in the ſecond Adam, thou neither knows law, reaſon, nor ſenſe:</hi> I ſay, It ſeems ſo by thy practiſe.</p>
               <p>Thou ſayes, <hi>Nothing brings forth Chriſt more as a Spirit of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom power and holineſs within thee unto good works, then when thou
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115288:14"/>
beholds him, as made righteouſneſs and ſanctification to thee without works.</hi> I ſay, ſtop thy mouth, and utter not thy confuſion; Is Chriſt made righteouſneſs and ſanctification to ſome without works? And is he now become the ſpirit of holineſs within thee unto good works, who hath ſo oft denied any thing within to be minded in heart or conſcience?</p>
               <p>Other lies thou tels, Of <hi>dyings and obedience in us, being made the way to juſtification in Chriſt, and that by my doctrine ne are ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified as much by the obedience of Paul, as by the man Chriſt:</hi> And ſuch like fulthy things, which follow thy own brain, and not my doctrine, neither can any honeſty gather any ſuch thing there. from, but the unclean ſpirit is vexed, that I deny a juſtification before faith and with out righteouſneſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning good works.</head>
               <p>ANd here thou charges me falſly alſo, As <hi>that I ſhould hold out the creature obedience unto the light, which reproves of ſin, and is bringing forth the fruits of it for good works, and for redemption:</hi> which is utterly falſe, for my account is that all ſhould wait in the light of Chriſt, and abide in it until the living word they come to hear and receive in their hearts, whereby the dead comes to be raiſed to life, which was dead in treſpaſſes and ſins, and that ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual man being quickened, the power of the Spirit brings forth in him the work of Gods righteouſneſs, which was from everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting; and this is another thing, than the Creature working, onely from that light that reproves ſin; ſo that my words doth exhort ſuch to ſtand ſtill till they ſee the ſalvation of God, and the word of his power revealed therein, by which he muſt be created or wrought into the good work, that he may walk there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.</p>
               <p>Another thing thou ſayes, that I ſay, <hi>the obedience or righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in Chriſt for juſtification and good works in us are one thing:</hi> I ſay, That the works of God and righteouſneſs in Chriſt are one thing from the beginning of the world, in Chriſt, in whom ever he is, according to its ſeveral meaſure and ends, but if thou in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend Creature works (though the moſt refined that ever was) I utterly deny them, and thy accuſation, as falſe like the reſt, and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:115288:14"/>
ſo having cleared the truth from thy ſlanders, and ſet it where it was, I ſhall come to thy doctrine.</p>
               <p>And thou ſpeaks of the everlaſting onely righteouſneſs upon all that beleive, and that <hi>it is as a ſpiritual heaven, large enough to take in and cover the ſecond creation:</hi> I ſay, that is true; But what is that to thee, that art in the firſt creation? It doth not cover thee, thy wickedneſs is ſeen, thy lies are laying open, thy nakedneſs appears, and thy folly to all men: Onely thou ſayeſt, <hi>thou reckoneſt thy ſelf to be ſo, though it be not ſo felt:</hi> I ſay, I know it, there were ever a generation that juſtified themſelves, but were not juſt before God, and thine will be found no other, who reckons thy ſelf juſtified by that which thou haſt neither ſeen, felt nor handled.</p>
               <p>And thou ſayes, <hi>Thou thinks it neceſſary to give warning, that all approaches unto, or converſes with the Majeſty and glory of God, by any redemption or operation, of whatſoever ſpirit or light within, where the redemption in the perſon of Chriſt is excluded.</hi> To which I ſay, Thou ſhews thy dark buſie mind, and what thou knows of approaches to God, or converſes with his majeſty and glory who imagines that that can be, where the redemption of Chriſt is excluded.</p>
               <p>Thou ſayes, <hi>But if any ask, how thou art redeemed while ſin is in thee?</hi> thou ſayeſt, <hi>the Father he laid your ſins upon Chriſt to take them away, and the Spirit bears witneſs that all things are finiſhed:</hi> I ſay, that is true where repentance and faith is, where by the creature denies himſelf and comes to Chriſt, there Chriſt takes the ſins away: But thy ſins are there yet, and thou a ſervant thereof, and the Spirit bears witneſs in the conſcience againſt thee for it, and the beſt way thou haſt to peace, is to ſtifle the witneſs of the Spirit in thy conſcience, and exhort others not to heed it.</p>
               <p>Thou ſayes, <hi>Through faith thou receives Chriſt into thy ſelf, and thou art received into him, and through this oneneſs art made righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, life and light:</hi> But how oft haſt thou denied this, or any thing within to be looked unto? Art thou now become righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, life and light thy ſelf, and was condemning it, as great error in me, in thy laſt to witneſs good works in Chriſt? Art thou become righteouſneſs thy ſelf, light and life, and wilt thou
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115288:15"/>
not allow another to teſtifie the works of Chriſt in him? Thy charity is either ſelfiſh, or thou knows not what thou ſayes, and ere thou go out of that page, thou contradicts it thy ſelf again, denies redemption by the operation of that Spirit that is within us, ſo that which makes thee righteouſneſs, life and light, by thy doctrine cannot work redemption; and thus thou tottereth to and fro, having undertaken a buſineſs, and would ſeem to ſay ſomething, and ſo being out of the light makes up a heap of confuſion.</p>
               <p>And as thou begins with a lie, ſo thou ends, ſaying, That I ſay, <hi>that all the works and meaſures performed by the Creature, in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the light within, do but all compleat the one work of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture redemption:</hi> And when thou haſt told this falſhood, thou ſets down a ſtory of <hi>Luther,</hi> wherein he divides <hi>Abraham</hi> and his righteouſneſs as far a ſunder as between heaven and earth: So to anſwer thee and thy ſtory, I ſhall produce one plain Scripture from <hi>James</hi> 2. from the 14. to the end of the Chapter. Was not thou even now telling of being made righteouſneſs into thy ſelf? and now brings a ſtory to divide <hi>Abrahams</hi> righteouſneſs as far from him as heaven from earth, and much ſuch ſtaggering thou makeſt, but the end of all is to keep righteouſneſs out of the door, that thy maſter may have liberty within.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning Election and Reprobation.</head>
               <p>ANd this thou begins to lay a foundation with a lie, and what thy building is like to be may be eaſily judged; Thou ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth I ſay, <hi>That the light in every man which reproves of ſin is Chriſt:</hi> And when thou haſt told that lie, and denied it again, then thou confeſſeſt what I ſay, that <hi>Chriſt is the elect ſeed;</hi> but dare not ſay, that any one is elected who is not in that ſeed, onely thou tels a blind ſtory, that <hi>thou was redeemed before thou was born;</hi> but art yet a ſervant of the devil, who was a liar from the beginning, and his works thou art doing, onely thou conceits thou art re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed, and ſuch a redemption the prophaneſt I know in the Nation claims it with thee (upon the ſame ground) and hath as good right as thou haſt for any thing yet thou haſt made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:115288:15"/>
               <head>Concerning the new Birth.</head>
               <p>HEre thou ſets on work in thy old manner, as one that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ceaſe from ſin:</p>
               <p>Firſt, Thou chargeth me to ſay, That <hi>by abiding in the ſeed or light within every man, thereby the old man is put off with his deeds.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>That I call the light the eternal Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>That I make the body and bloud of Chriſt no more but a figure of the body and bloud within, that is the light within all men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, <hi>And that my end is to preſs through unto God by an Atonement and mediation to be made in our bodies, that is, obedience to the light within.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And when thou haſt told theſe four horrible lies on me, then thou goes on in thy doctrine, but dare not gain ſay one word of what I have written, but runs into thy old confuſion, and ſayes, <hi>The new Creature is not a Jew, ſeeking ſalvation in the letter or Conſcience, nor a Gentile, worſhipping God by the light;</hi> and ſayes, <hi>the worlds light is a candle from the Lord, ſaying, do this and live:</hi> And divers more ſuch confuſions, which hath no truth in them, neither haſt thou any proof for them; with ſundry accuſations and ſlanders thou goes on, which are nothing to the purpoſe as to the thing in hand; and having forme ly denied them, I ſhall not here rake in them, but let them not with thee.</p>
               <p>Then thou ſpeaks of perſecution, thou ſayeſt, <hi>They that follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed after the Spirit and teachings thereof, were alwayes perſecuted by the children of the letter:</hi> Where thou might read thy ſelf, were not thou blind, who art breathing out all theſe lies againſt us, for owning Chriſt &amp; his light within us for our teacher &amp; guide, for which thy miſcheivous mind would make people believe we deny the perſon of Chriſt, becauſe we own him in ſpirit, when in truth none can own his perſon but who ſees him in the light, the reſt are the children of the letter, and hath no miniſtration elſe to know Chriſt by; who can imagine from the Hiſtory, but are void of the Myſtery, which is held in a pure conſcience, and not in a book without, which myſtery thou that denies all in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:115288:16"/>
art void on, who falſly ſayes, <hi>The light in the conſcience is the ſame with the Law in the letter.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning Baptiſm, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>ANd thou ſayes, my profeſſion herein is, <hi>That the baptiſm of Chriſt thou underſtands the light within all men.</hi> But from what doſt thou underſtand it? for by me it was never ſpoken nor thought: ſo that its from thy dark ſpirit that cannot under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand to ſpeak true, and ſo given to lies; was there ever ſuch a pack of lies heaped together? as though thou hadſt reſolved not to ſpeak a true ſentence, in whatever thou ſpeaks of me; for this ſhall appear, that not one of thy Charges hitherto are truth, or what I ſpoke, but thou haſt made lies, and then diſproves them, ſhewing thy art and trading to be onely there, for the truth I write ſtands ſtill untouched.</p>
               <p>And notwithſtanding all this filth, thou tels us of a myſtery we know not, that is, That <hi>you were waſhed, ſanctified and juſtified before you were:</hi> Which indeed is non ſenſe and a lie, to ſay, that which is not can be waſhed, or ſanctified, or juſtified; and in that ſenſe it is a myſtery indeed. But whatever was before thou were, thou art now a ſervant of Satan, and his work thou doſt, and art not waſhed from thy wickedneſs. And if the waſhing and juſtifying of a thing that is not can juſtifie thee in thy wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, this is a large faith; its no wonder though thou be ſo bold in thy wickedneſs. Yet this I ſay, its a late invented faith (to wit) that waſhing nothing will make thee clean. For the Saints waſhing, ſanctifying and juſtifying was when they had forſaken their ſins, and without waſhing from their ſins which they had committed, they could not enter into the Kingdom of God, read 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 9, 10, 11. And their way to waſhing was to walk in the light, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1. 7. a thing the devil and his dark born brood loves not above all that can be named, any other conjurations or imaginations they will own, but away with the light, thats an error, that deſerves not to live.</p>
               <p>But the beleiving of this, thou ſayes, <hi>ſprinkles from your hearts an evil conſcience;</hi> that is, indeed though you ſin it troubles not your hearts, you beleive that you was waſhed and juſtified be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:115288:16"/>
you was begotten or born, and once juſtified alwayes juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſo you make no conſcience what you do, that is the evil that troubles your conſcience when you ſin, but your faith hath ſprinkled you from that evil conſcience, and now you have no more conſcience of ſin, for that in the conſcience, that is pure and teſtifies againſt ſin, is but legal, and you are not under the Law, but under Grace; and this is a myſtery that tender con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences knows not, and ſo are but weak and fooliſh, and under bondage; but you are grown Chriſtians, grown in the faith above ſuch folly; when indeed it is but the Ranter that is got up and joyned with the Devil, in a deſign to caſt off the yoak, and get liberty for the beaſt that cannot endure the croſs, and ſo hath deviſed away with the old Murtherer to ſlay the Witneſſes, and then make merry over them. You have a myſtery none know but your ſelves; other fools, that knows not your faith, ſtands to repent of their ſins if they ſin, and cannot be at peace till God ſpeak peace in their conſcience; but your ſin was par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned before you was born, and you are not ſo fooliſh to make conſcience of it now; you will have no more of that conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence for ſin, you was once purged from ſin, when you were not, and can ſin now under that which God once did in Chriſt; to think ſo, was to deny the perſon of the man Chriſt Jeſus, who hath done all that belongs to you one thouſand ſix hundred years ſince. And now to fear, that any thing you can do in your per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons can make that ineffectual, were great unbelief, and legal, and bondage of ſpirit; and if this be not your faith and the effects of it let both thy judgment in thy book, and thy pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe witneſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the Lords Supper.</head>
               <p>ANd in this I muſt not eſcape thy tongue, charging me to ſay that I have not ſpoken; yet not ſo quite contrary to my intent as in the others; yet things that are utterly falſe haſt thou caſt on the truth; As <hi>that we eſteem the eating the fleſh of Chriſt but a moral thing:</hi> And <hi>that the Goſpel-myſtery is with us become a doctrine of bare morality, &amp;c.</hi> Things deviſed in thy own heart. And thou ſayes, <hi>To ſee God in all things, to diſcern him as the body
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:115288:17"/>
and vertue of all Creatures, and to uſe all things in moderation, is no more than Pagan divinity.</hi> Is this all the effect and end of the bloud of Chriſt? I ſay, that is not all the end and effect of his bloud, but it is one good effect, and a great deal more than yet it hath wrought in thee; thou doeſt not yet ſee God in all things, unleſs thou wilt ſay thou ſees him in lying ſlandering and curſed ſpeaking. And that thou and thy Proſclites are not come to uſe all things in moderation, let your pride, covetouſneſs and exceſs be witneſs againſt you, &amp; he thou a vitneſs againſt thy ſelf, and the reſt of thy Ranting crew, who uſe the bloud of Chriſt for an occaſion to the fleſh, and a cloak for your liberty therein, that Pagan divintiy is better than yours; and if the Pagan divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity bring forth theſe fruits, which your divinity doth not, I ſhall ſay as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid concerning the Gentiles, They are the beleivers who bring forth the fruits of faith, and you are the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fidels, who juſtifie your ſelves before either faith or works, and without them. But did the Apoſtle teach Pagan divinity, when he ſaid, <hi>Let your moderation be known to all men, the Lord is at hand, Phil.</hi> 4. 5? And did Chriſt teach Pagan divinity, when he ſaid, <hi>Take heed leaſt at any time your hearts be overcharged with ſurfeiting and drunkenneſs and cares of this life, and ſo that day come upon you unawares? Luke</hi> 21. 34 Was theſe Pagans that taught this, or are they Pagans who ſee God in all things? I ſhall rather chuſe to be numbred amongſt thoſe Pagans, than to be one of thy Beleivers, ſelf-juſtified without either faith or works.</p>
               <p>Thou ſayeſt, <hi>Whoeuer looks into the myſtery of Chriſts death, may ſee the firſt</hi> Adam, <hi>with all his deeds, and the world, with all its works, &amp; all old things done away</hi> I ſay, be witneſs againſt thy ſelf, that thou never ſaw that myſtery, in whom the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> with the worlds works, and old things are yet alive</p>
               <p>Thou ſayeſt. <hi>The Lord ordained the Supper for a rudiment to all that ſhould have need thereof.</hi> It ſeems thou judges ſome to have no need of it; but was not thou condemning me even now for ſaying, diſcerning him to be the body, and vertue of all Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and to ſee God in all things, and looking at this as too baſe to be the the effects of that Supper? and is the Supper it ſelf now become a rudiment with thee?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:115288:17"/>
And thou goeſt on to tell what this rudiment muſt be, and <hi>that therein is not a bare ſpeculation of Chriſt or the divinity, as filling all things, for the natural man may know ſo much,</hi> thou ſaies; <hi>but to deſcern the law and all perfection, to be already buried and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed in his grave, and your ſelves raiſed up into liberty,</hi> &amp;c. I ſay it is true, lawleſs liberty is the thing that thy Miniſtery prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and to bury perfection; but the end why Chriſt ſent forth his Miniſters, was for perfecting the Saints, not to bury perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4 11, 12, 13. And the Saints Preached Chriſt for their Law-giver, and the Law for their hearers to look into and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue therein, not to be hearers onely, but doers of the work; and ſaid they ſhould be bleſſed in that deed, and ſaid the Law was Perfect and did endure for ever, theſe did not bury it but preach it and live in it, and was ſet free by it, <hi>James</hi> 1. 25. <hi>Rom</hi> 8. 2. But thy way is to bury it out of the ſight, and all perfection with it, leſt it trouble thy liberty, and this is the end of thy rudiment, and yet ſayeſt, the natural man, may know the ſpeculation of Chriſt or the divinity; I ſay, could he know that, (which is falſe as Scripture witneſſes, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 14.) I ſhould chuſe the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall mans eſtate, far before thine and thy liberty, for all thou haſt got with thy rudiment, wherewith thou haſt buried the Law and all perfection.</p>
               <p>Another piece of thy doctrine, is, <hi>That Chriſt revealed in man, is not to reconcile the Creatures unto himſelf.</hi> I ſay, the Devil would have the creatures act his command, to ſpend upon his luſt, and therefore would exclude Chriſt in man, to be but as ſome Cypher or ſomething to take on, not to have any power in the heart, to take the creatures from their luſt, and bring them into the place and Covenant wherein they were created, and that in the heart of every man particularly; (which is not done where he is not in the heart:) he would be content to allow him a name or a talk of reconciling people, before they be begotten or born, (as thy faith is) but after they come into the world and be able to do him any ſervice, then muſt he have the ordering of all with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and to own Chriſt for a Redeemer in the heart, daily to free him from his ſins, while the creature lives, that muſt go under the name of an error, if the Devil be teacher: and to affright ſimple people the more from it, he tells them, that to wait upon Chriſt
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:115288:18"/>
in ſpirit every day, to redeem them from their preſent ſins, and enlighten them, and let them ſee his preſent wiles, with which every day he beſets them, this is to deny his perſon, and what he did at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and is but a ſpirit of fear, they need not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble themſelves withall; Its enough that Chriſt reconciled the world in himſelf, and ruled over the Devil in his own perſon, he need not do the ſame in him, that is but to do the work over a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine; and with ſuch deceirs as theſe, he deceives the ſimplicity, and ſets the beaſt at liberty, and having got up in one, and the falſe Prophet thereon, which hath told the lies, there Anti chriſt goeth out into the world, to oppoſe the word of reconciliation, or the government of Chriſt in the hearts of all the reſt.</p>
               <p>Thou ſayeſt, <hi>That my ſaying Chriſt was not born in the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples when the Supper was appointed, is contrary to truth:</hi> But truth faith, that the Holy Ghoſt was not yet given, becauſe that Juſus Chriſt was not yet glorified, <hi>John</hi> 7. 39. neither was Chriſt born in all in the Churches, for ſome was carnal, and they was but waiting for his appearance, and many of them knew not the Table of the Lord from the Table of Devils, and ſo was not come ſo far as thoſe thou calls Pagans, to ſee God in every thing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning Redemption.</head>
               <p>ANd here thou begins firſt to make a lie as formerly, to make thy ſelf work, ſaying that I ſay, <hi>Redemption is not of ſinners, but of the light within:</hi> which is but the falſhood of thine owne heart, for I ſpeak of that ſeed that lyeth ſlain in treſpaſſes and ſins, and in redemption of that is the ſinner redeemed, who was cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivated into ſin and condemnation with the other ſeed of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, which is not to be redeemed but deſtroyed.</p>
               <p>And after this lie, thou tells of my darkneſs, and cries out, <hi>how are the abundant riches of grace, the fulneſs of the Mediator, and the power of the Croſſe reſolved at once into the light?</hi> I ſay, blind man, when was they out of it? yet doth none ſee them there but as they follow in the light, come to ſee the life, as ſaith Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 8. 12. ſo that every one that ſees the light, ſees not them; but he that follows the light, ſees and receaves them therein, which are not to be received in any thing elſe: But how
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:115288:18"/>
ſhouldeſt thou know what is in the light, who denies all light, both within and without, whatſoever, to be exerciſed therein? Children of darkneſs could never judge what was in the light, who in thy blind mind art telling, that the ſeed needs no redemption: what was that that was redeemed in the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> which was dead in treſpaſſes and ſins, in which they walked before they received the Apoſtles doctrine, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1. 1, 2. was they naturally dead, or the ſeed of God was ſlain in them? but when thou knows what that is that is dead in thee, whileſt thou art alive in the Devills works, denying any thing in thee to ſave the therefrom, then thou ſhalt know what ſeed that is I ſpeak of, which is not the ſeed of the evil doer, till then ſtop thy mouth from ſpeaking thou knows not what, who haſt denied all light whatſoever, what art thou like to know, but what darkneſs teacheth thee?</p>
               <p>Thou goes on in thy confuſed mind, and tells of a greater law that came forth, <hi>Chriſt in fleſh,</hi> and of <hi>an end put both to law and fleſh by the body of Chriſt,</hi> and that <hi>you are joined to Chriſt alone according to the inward man; ye dwell in the curtains of</hi> Solomon, <hi>and liberty and reſt of Chriſt, but according to the fleſh, you are in the tents of</hi> Keder: And yet thy greateſt work in thy book, is to deny chriſt according to the in ward man, and to ſet up the knowledge of him according to the fleſh; and thus with thy drunken dark ſpirit thou confounds thy ſelf, and ſtaggers to and fro at noon day, vomiting out thy own ſhame and confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>Thou tells alſo, that thy <hi>Redemption, no law nor light of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience can deſcern, but the light of Chriſt ſhining into the heart:</hi> So in thy opinion, the light of Chriſt in the heart is no law, nor light of conſcience, what is the law of the ſpirit of life, if not the light of Chriſt in the heart? and what is that which is good in the conſcience, the anſwer whereof ſaves, if not the light of Chriſt? And doſt not thou ſay in thy 55. page, <hi>That all that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve are juſtified from all things, by the law of the ſpirit accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the conſcience, from which they could not be juſtified by the law of Moſes?</hi> And is it now become, that no law nor light of conſcience can deſcern it? ſo people muſt be juſtified by they do not know what; and much like according to thy doctrine, who affirms they are juſtified before they be begotten or born; then
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:115288:19"/>
are not like to diſcern what their redemption is, nor what it is that is redeemed, from what nor by whom, further than by a talk from a drunken ſpirit.</p>
               <p>Thou ſaies further, <hi>There is no myſtery in the light within:</hi> I ſay, where was that myſtery that was held in a pure conſcience, which the Apoſtle ſpeaks on, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 9. was not that within? but thou haſt found out a greater myſtery, than the myſtery of faith, that is, that the thing that is not, may be waſhed, ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and juſtified, thou may well ſay this is above all the myſtery within, and indeed beyond all faith that is of God, onely thy imaginations hath no limit, whoſe foundation is in the air. Thou tells of a greater and better eſtate than <hi>Adam</hi> in his innocencie, which is no more but in thy imaginations; for thou that never knew the life of innocencie in thy ſelf, as it was in <hi>Adam,</hi> art far unlike to know a greater, wherefore ſtop thy mouth vain bab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler, out of which comes all this confuſion, ſmoak and darkneſs, and with the light of thy conſcience find thy own meaſure, and boaſt not above it, ſo will thou ſee thy ſelf for all thy boaſting, to be as dumb as thoſe <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeaks of, as to the ſtate of innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, or any ſtate above it witneſſed in thee, or thou in it, further than an airie notion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning Justification, Sanctification, Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification.</head>
               <p>ANd this is not without a ſlander like the reſt, but thy lies are ſo many, I am weary with raking in them; ſo to thy doctrine.</p>
               <p>And thou tells of a juſtification, already prepared and wrought for ſinners upon the Croſſe, when he bare away your ſins and death, and all the evils of this world, and thou ſayeſt, <hi>He that can but truly believe this, according to his faith, ſo is it done.</hi> But art thou not now become partial, who haſt aſſumed a privilege to thy ſelf that thou wilt allow no body elſe? who ſayeſt, thou thy ſelf art juſtified, and ſin waſhed away, before either faith or works, yea before thou thy ſelf were, and now haſt put others upon believing for juſtification, and ſaieſt, <hi>ſo it is done, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:115288:19"/>
to their faith, and thine done without faith, yea, before either faith or works.</p>
               <p>And ſeeing thou limits the time of this work of juſtification onely to that time, when Chriſt was upon a carnal croſs, and ſayeſt, <hi>Thou wert justified before thou wast:</hi> Then when was all juſtified that died before the outward crucifying of Chriſt? If there was not juſtification in Chriſt before that time, then either muſt it follow, that the Saints that died before was juſtified ſince they died, or elſe are all condemned? But if every particular Saint was juſtified in their time, by that everlaſting righteouſneſs of God, by faith in Chriſt Jeſus, and all that departed from that righteouſneſs, was to periſh, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18. Then muſt it either fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſo row, or juſtification is not the ſame that it was, which do thou ſhew if thou canſt wherein it differs further then they (by faith) in him that was to come, whom they ſaw by faith, and we in faith of him that did come, whom we now ſee by faith in a clearer manifeſtation, but both in the ſame everlaſting righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of God, without which righteouſneſs by faith in them, and they in it, without which neither they nor we can enter into the Kingdom.</p>
               <p>A Queſtion thou asks, <hi>But can there be reſt and liberty where there is a groaning for it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thy anſwer is, <hi>Yea, oh man, as well as</hi> Paul <hi>could be preſent in ſpirit where he was abſent in body.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſay, Thy compariſon will not hold, for <hi>Paul</hi> was really pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in ſpirit, and he need not groan for it, but he that imagines a liberty, and yet is the ſervant of ſin, is not ſo; and how be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at reſt, and travelling and groaning to come to reſt, can ſtand together, a little ſimplicity may judge thereof.</p>
               <p>Thou ſayeſt, <hi>The love of God, and righteouſneſs of Chriſt, are not more or leſs for the beleiver.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſay, That is the ground of all the Ranters, and as they are in God himſelf, without relation to any particular, they are no more or leſs.</p>
               <p>But in relation to mans ſalvation, he that believes not ſhall never have benefit by them, according to his faith ſo ſhall he receive, as thou thy ſelf, but now, confeſſed, with whom its no
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:115288:20"/>
new thing to ſay, and unſay, both with a wind.</p>
               <p>Thou tels of thy being juſtified by Chriſt thy head, but the manifeſtation of it in thy ſelf, therein, is thy ſanctification, and before thou ſaid, Thou <hi>was ſanctified before thou was born, and before thou wert:</hi> Thus thy Potſheards are claſhing one againſt another, who art lifting up thy ſelf againſt the Iron Rod, and in oppoſition to the light of the world.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the Law.</head>
               <p>THy Charge here is made up moſt of thy own words, and not mine, and ſo as thy own, and not mine, I ſhall paſs it.</p>
               <p>And thou begins thy doctrine with a deceit alſo, ſaying, <hi>Are the Law and Goſpel the ſame?</hi> As though I had ſaid they was, and thus with deceit and falſhood thou carries on thy work, ſaying, that I ſay, <hi>They know not his Commands in Spirit, who ſay, that Chriſt fulfilled the Law for us in his own Perſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another deceit is, That <hi>Whereas I ſay the bloud of Buls and Goats made nothing perfect, &amp;c.</hi> This thou turns to the bloud of Chriſt, as though I denied it to make perfect; and ſo runs on from one falſe deceit to another, for if thy deceit fall, thy works is at an end, the whole body being little elſe.</p>
               <p>And when thou haſt caſt out thy lies, then thou comes to thy faith, that is, <hi>That Chriſt hath ſuſtained all the Law hath to charge upon you, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But let me ask thee one queſtion with thy large faith, Who was redeemed and juſtified before thou was born; Suppoſe thou commit adultery, or murther, will not the Law charge that ſin upon thee, that Law God hath written in thy heart, Yea, and ſo as, without new waſhing, to condemn thee at the day of Judgment? If thou ſay yea, then thy juſtification and waſhing before thou wert born, may be diſanulled, and ſtand in need of the bloud now: If thou ſay no, I ſay I ſhould be loath to have to do with any one of thy opinion, I am ſure no Ranter hath a larger.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:115288:20"/>
Thou tels a ſtory of being dead in Chriſt unto the firſt <hi>Adam, with all his deeds, and all the evils that came in by him; And as thou beholds Christ thou art changed into the ſame Image from glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to glory.</hi> I ſay, if lying and deceit be a deed of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> then, I ſay, thou art alive to that, and it raigns in thee. And whereas thou ſayes, As <hi>thou beholds him thou art changed into his Image. &amp;c.</hi> I ſay, even ſo, for thou who haſt denied him in thee never beheld him, and ſo art the ſame thou waſt, and deceit is thy glory, and from one deceit to another is thy charge: And thou that was pure before thou waſt born, and ſayes, that is thy ſtate thou ſtands in, what needs thou any more changing?</p>
               <p>Another way thou would take to defraud the Scripture, that thereby thou mayeſt keep any from looking for waſhing or ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifying now; ſayes thou, <hi>When it is ſaid, we are juſtified by God and by Grace, by the name of Chriſt, by the Spirit of our God, we are to underſtand that theſe went out againſt our ſins in the bloud of Chriſt:</hi> and ſo would make all theſe of no uſe now in our age, as to ſanctifie now; but who reads the Saints teſtimony, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 11. may find, that they was waſhed, ſanctified and juſtified after they had ſinned, and not before, as thou imagins thou waſt before thou was born; and ſo thy waſhing ſo far before hand leaves thee filthy ſtill, but they was waſhed from their filthineſs, and knew no liar nor falſe accuſer muſt enter into the Kingdom of Heaven, how clear ſoever they was before they was born, and before they were, a waſhing and juſtification thou ſo much boaſts on; but its clear, they and thou art not of one juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for theirs was preſent, thine before thou waſt; theirs by faith, thine before faith; theirs by the ſpirit, thine by imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, without either ſpirit, faith, or knowledge.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:115288:21"/>
               <head>Concerning Chriſt Jeſus.</head>
               <p>THis is the firſt Charge that is made up of truth.</p>
               <p>And thou ſayes my faith is, <hi>That Chriſt humbled himſelf and became obedient unto death, that he might become a living ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, &amp;c.</hi> And this thou oppoſes as an error, which are the words of Scripture. And though thou have ſaid true in thy firſt charge, yet it muſt not paſs without a lie in thy anſwer, that is, as though I had ſaid, <hi>That the myſtery of faith is become no more with us than a lofty imagination of reaſon:</hi> when there is not one word by me to that purpoſe, but thy own vomit caſt out upon us to make the truth odious, which thou canſt not otherwiſe diſprove. So thou adds a confuſion or two, and leaves what I have ſaid as it was.</p>
               <p>Firſt, thou ſayes, <hi>Not the light within is that which leads to Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> and ſo would make Chriſt a liar like thy ſelf, <hi>John</hi> 8. 12, And then thou ſayes, <hi>It muſt be known by the Spirit;</hi> and ſo makes thy ſelf a liar if the Spirit be light within, which none that ever knew it will ſay otherwiſe of it.</p>
               <p>Thou ſayes alſo, <hi>That the Scriptures are the Image of Chriſt:</hi> A thing they may beleive that will, for ought thou proves of it.</p>
               <p>Thou asks, <hi>Would the light within have ſhewed you the Atone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp;c?</hi> I ſay, the true Atonement it will, and no other thing can ſhew it to every particular perſon; but thy atonement, that was before thou was born, and is yet in thy ſin, it will not, it ſhews no ſuch lies; but blind man, may not all that have any experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of atonement ſee what thy atonement is, that is not ſeen within? hadſt thou been reconciled to God in thy heart and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, the liars mouth had been ſtopt; but if thou ſhould own ſuch an atonement, thou would loſe thy Maſters ſervice.</p>
               <p>But didſt thou know what atonement or unity with God is, thou could not feed thy ſelf with lies, taking conceits for atone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, while that of God within in thy Conſcience condemns thee, but thy atonement would be to ſee the light of his counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:115288:21"/>
ſhining in thy heart, in the face of Jeſus, and ſee him ſpeak peace, who wounds.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the Miniſtry of Chriſt.</head>
               <p>THis Charge is true alſo; That I ſay, <hi>The Miniſters of Chriſt have the word in them, that they preach not for hire, that they are perſecuted, &amp;c.</hi> and this thou likes not for truth.</p>
               <p>And to oppoſe it thou ſayes, firſt, <hi>I ſay rightly; but Miniſters of Righteouſneſneſs are of Satan or of Chriſt, zealouſly to affect, to preach frecly, ſuffer labour, ſtripes, impriſonments, &amp;c.</hi> I ſay, Are Miniſters of Righteouſneſs of Satan, and do the Miniſters of Satan preach freely, &amp;c? Then take notice, that thou liar and hireling never yet came ſo far as a Miniſter of Satan in thy own account; and thus inſtead of weighing us thou haſt weighed thy ſelf, and all thy brethren the Pariſh Maſters with thee, and art found wanting of Miniſters of Satan; for ſhame now ceaſe calling your ſelves Miniſters of Chriſt, if by your fruits you may be known, and Chriſt hath ſaid you muſt, <hi>Math.</hi> 7. 16, 20. but this thou denies, and ſayes, <hi>Nay, by their ſpirits they muſt be judged, and their ſpirit by their words;</hi> So the Devil would come in for a Miniſter, who can get words enough, but fruits he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, therefore he loves not that trial.</p>
               <p>Thou further ſayes, Thou <hi>art jealous that we are Miniſters of darkneſs:</hi> Yet not ſo dark, but we can through the light of Chriſt ſee the Devils deceits, and thats thy puniſhment at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning Free-Will.</head>
               <p>THis Charge is falſly made up, not as I have ſpoken all the words in it, yet ſomewhat of truth there is in it.</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>The light within which reproves the evill deeds is the will of God, by which will we are ſanctified: That in every man which
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:115288:22"/>
ſhews ſin, and reproves for it, is free grace: This light in every man is Free. Will:</hi> Which is utterly falſe, for I have not ſaid, that every man that ſees this light hath Free-will, but with the light he may ſee the will of God, which is free, from his own will, but none hath Free-will but who denies their own wils.</p>
               <p>Thy anſwer is, <hi>That if the firſt be ſo, then is the death of Chriſt of none effect.</hi> So that by thy doctrine, if it be the will of God, that men ſhould be reproved of ſin by the light of Chriſt; and if it be by the will of God, that we are ſanctified and ſaved (for that is the thing I affirm) then Chriſt died in vain, this is thy conſequence; ſo I ſhall prove what I affirm, and then ſee all men what thy doctrine of conſequence is.</p>
               <p>That it is the will of God, that all men ſhould be reproved for their evil deeds by the light, read <hi>Epheſians 5. 13. John 16. 8.</hi> And that by the will of God we are ſanctified and ſaved, <hi>Hebrews 10. 9, 10. 1 Theſ. 4. 3. 1 Tim. 2. 4.</hi> Theſe with many other Scriptures will prove what I have ſaid, prove thy conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence as thou canſt.</p>
               <p>Thou ſayes alſo, <hi>If the ſecond be ſo, then the Law and free grace is the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So by thy doctrine and conſequence, if that Comforter Chriſt ſpeaks on, which reproves the world of ſin, and the light of Chriſt, be free grace, then the law and free Grace are the ſame; a ſtrange conſequence, like the former. Is not the light of the world free grace? <hi>John 8. 12. John 16. 8.</hi> and the Spirit of God free grace? If that be not, then what is, ſeeing Chriſt and the Spirit is denied?</p>
               <p>Further ſayeſt thou, <hi>If the light God hath put into all men be the gift of grace, the gift of heavenly righteouſneſs by Chriſt, wherein is the end of the law and ſin heeded?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſay, what thou intends by thy conſequence, &amp; by ſin heeded, let the Reader judge if he can; but that the light is the gift of grace, that I own and wert not thou blind, thou would not ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine any light of God given to man, which is not the gift of grace, it muſt either be of grace or of works; and what work haſt thou done to obtain the gift of Chriſt light?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:115288:22"/>
Thou ſayes, <hi>If the third be ſo then there is that in the natural man, whereby he is able to know and receive the things of the Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſay, Thy Charge in this is a lie, not my words, and thy conſequence is of the ſame vote, and ſo to thee I leave them, being thy own work, to ſay and gaineſay; but that the light of Chriſt, who ever minds it and follow it, is able to lead to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the things of the Spirit, that I have proved, <hi>John</hi> 8. 12. and divers other places.</p>
               <p>Another deceit to caſt a miſt over the light is; thou ſayes, <hi>The deep things of God, his grace in Chriſt, ſparkling in the old time now in one promiſe, now in another, and foretold by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets (whereof the Righteouſneſs of the Fews Philoſophers and Grecks knew nothing) this cannot be diſcovered by the cleareſt light in the natural man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſay, Here are two deceits covered in this, firſt, as though none of the Jews or Saints did diſcern this before Chriſt came at <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> the ſecond, as though the cleareſt light, with which Chriſt enlightneth men within, could not lead to the diſcerning of him; which are both contrary to Chriſts words, who ſaith, <hi>Abraham ſaw my day,</hi> and to the Prophets he was born, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 9. 6. And ſaith Chriſt, <hi>I am the light of the world, he that follows me ſhall have the light of life, John</hi> 8. 12. And ſo with the words of truth thy miſt is driven away, and the truth cleared from thy deceits.</p>
               <p>And then as thou begun thy work with lies, ſo thou ends, with two lies more thou caſts upon us. That <hi>we level the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of the ſecond</hi> Adam, <hi>and the reſtoring of all things in him, to be no other thing but Law and Reaſon.</hi> Secondly, <hi>That we make the death of Chriſt of none effect, and the whole mystery of grace in him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But ſeeing thou doſt falſly ſlander us herein, I ſhall ſtate the caſe truly as it is in this Queſtion; Whether they that believe Chriſt died at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and witneſs his bloud in them, whereby their hearts are ſprinkled, and waſhed from lying, deceit, and pride, and uncleanneſs, by the in-dweiling of Chriſt in them, ſo kept according to the meaſure of Chriſt
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:115288:23"/>
revealed in Spirit? Or they who ſay, that Chriſt died at <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> but deny him in them to redeem and ſave them from the power of ſin, or his bloud in them to ſprinkle and waſh them daily from dead works? Or any light of his whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, either within or without, to be exerciſed in, to freedom and perfection, but ſay, they were waſhed, ſanctified and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified before they came into the world, but in the world are found liars, and falſe accuſers, and deceitful teachers: this being the true caſe between thee and us, I leave it to the wiſe to judge, who it is that denies Chriſt Jeſus the everlaſting Prieſt, which abideth for evermore, to every generation; and who it is that makes his bloud of none effect, as to waſh away ſin, and to reſtore all things to God; and whether the effect of the bloud of Chriſt be to take away ſin, or to talk on, whereby to plead for ſin againſt the preſent being and effect thereof (to wit) to keep out of the Devils works? Now who owns the bloud of Chriſt let the effect manifeſt to all men. And know thou, that the bloud of Chriſt is not words not imaginations, of what thou never ſee before thou was born, but a living ſubſtance, which is to be known, with its effect, to every particular Saint in every generation, and ſuch, who ſay they are ſaved by the bloud of Chriſt before they were, but now are found in their ſins, are ſuch as deny the bloud of Chriſt, and to them they make it of none effect, who are not waſhed; and they who ſay, they was purged, ſanctified and juſtified before they were, and now when they are, are unclean, boaſts of that they never ſaw, and truſts in a lie, for talking what Chriſt was by the hiſtory is one thing, which all have and believe, and yet abide in condemnation, and without further may periſh; but to learn Chriſt in the myſtery, of faith, which is held in a pure Conſcience, is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and onely ſuch know him aright, both what he did at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and the end of it, who follow him now in ſpirit, and have fellowſhip in his death and ſufferings, and ſo at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains to his reſurrection in the ſpirit and life, and ſo follow in his life and righteouſneſs, ſuch onely confeſs him, and ſhall not therein be condemned.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:115288:23"/>
Much more might be ſaid to lay open thy deceits in thy other part of thy book, but my life is not to rifle in ſuch heaps of confuſion, were it not that I am forced to it, for clearing the truth from falſe Teachers, who are wholly igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the myſtery of faith, which is held in a pure Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and ſo know nought but in the natural comprehenſions, as brute beaſts, judging of the great myſtery of God and his redemption to ſtand in viſibles and carnal things, times and places, which things in their carnal wiſdom they make uſe on, to fight againſt the ſpiritual appearance of Chriſt in the Creature, without which there can be neither life nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption. No, Chriſt himſelf, onely known after the fleſh, brings no man to God, but Chriſt revealed in ſpirit from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, that everlaſting Light and Glory of the Father, the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Spirit, and Comforter, that could not come till he went away in the fleſh. And if his preſence was not the full ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of the great promiſe of the Father and the Son, but he muſt go away in the fleſh, out of their carnal ſight, no more to be in the world carnally, but in them ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually, which is the Comforter, even the Spirit of truth, to guide them into all truth; and this Chriſt holds forth as their greater power and comfort. Yea, and when they had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him ſo, they ſaid, though they had known Chriſt after the fleſh, they knew him ſo no more: how much leſs is a talk of him whom you never ſee, neither with out nor within, with his preſence in ſpirit, which is the main end why he came in the fleſh in his own perſon, that through faith in him, who was the firſt begotten from the dead, he might appear in ſpirit in all his, and dwell in them, guide and govern in them for ever, as his dwelling place in this world from generation to gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration for evermore, in which body he is vailed from the worlds wiſdom now as ever he was, and in whom he now ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers as he hath ever done: I ſay, how much ſhort ſuch are of the knowledge of a living Chriſt, his preſence or redemption, theſe times may judge, and the fruits thereof, for where Chriſt is, the body is dead, becauſe of ſin, and the ſpirit is life be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of righteouſneſs; but where a talk of Chriſt onely is
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:115288:24"/>
the body of ſin lives, ſuch would murther him where he is come, under a pretence of their denying Chriſt at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> when they do not onely believe what he did there, but alſo witneſs him in them their Saviour at preſent from ſin and the power of Satan, which is the end why he came at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and with out which the other ſaves not.</p>
               <p>And for this haſt thou ſetup thy horn againſt it, and haſt brought out this heap of confuſion to ſhew thy ſelf blind, with the reſt of thy earth born brethren, who are at ſtrife one with another, but now joyned together in open battel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the light of the Lamb, which is riſen to reveal your dark foundation, and that your curious <hi>Babel</hi> may become a heap of rubbiſh, till there be not left a way in, nor our, nor a place to hide you.</p>
               <p>And ſuch a heap there of is in the other part of thy book as might fill a volume to repeat and anſwer; but the ſubſtance thereof being anſwered in this foregoing, or in other books, I ſhall ſay little, onely give thee and the world a veiw of ſome few of thy errors, and let the Scripture reprove them, ſuch as theſe following.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>Errors.</head>
                  <item>THat there are three way to know God, when as there is but one way, even Chriſt from the beginning, though in ſeveral Miniſtrations, <hi>John</hi> 14. 6.</item>
                  <item>That the knowledge of God, according to the Law, is Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry; whereas God hath ſaid, <hi>I will write my Law in your hearts, and you ſhall know me,</hi> which is the new Covenant, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was it ever Idolatry to know God after the Law, <hi>Heb. 8. 8, 9, 10, 11. Jer. 31. 32, 34. Jam. 1. 25.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>That the Doctrine of Devils doth preach a Jeſus, Goſpel, and Spirit, <hi>2 Cor. 3. 16, 17.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>That all men know God according to his Godhead, <hi>Mat. 11, 27. 1 Cor. 15. 34. 2 Theſ. 1. 8.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>That a Man, while encloſed encloſed up in a body of ſin and death, is at the ſame time raiſed up into the heavenly Righteouſneſs,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:115288:24"/>
Immortality and freedom, above all ſin or ſhadow of evil, <hi>Math. 6. 24. Rom. 6. 16. John 8. 34, 35, 36. Rom. 8. 12.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>That Chriſt cannot be ſeen, by the obedience of the Spirit, within us, <hi>1 Cor. 12. 3. Rom. 8. 14.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>That thoſe whoſe root and foundation is, what Chriſt is, and hath done in himſelf, but the way to partake of the benefit of it is their union with him; ſuch do (by luſt) crucifie his Spirit and Grace within, <hi>John</hi> 15 4, 5.</item>
                  <item>That the Goſpel, being a Myſtery of things hid in Chriſt, is neither written, nor to be ſeen in the heart of man, <hi>1 Tim. 3. 9. Rom. 10, 8, 9, 10.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>That the Goſpel, as a Commandement and Peice of mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, may be read and beleived by every man, and yet ſayes in another place, the Goſpel is hid from all principles of fleſh, <hi>2 Cor. 4. 3, 4.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>That the Myſtery of God in Chriſt is not to be known by his enlightening within men, <hi>2 Cor 4. 6, 7.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>That the Spirit ſet up aſunder from the letter, brings forth a twofold error, both perilous and hurtful, <hi>2 Cor. 3. 6. Rom. 7. 6.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>That affirming the Light in the Conſcience the way or guide to Chriſt, is a darkſom and fleſhly principle, wherein Chriſt and his Redemption is forgotten for ever, <hi>1 Tim. 1. 19.</hi> and 3. 9.</item>
                  <item>That all juſt Laws of Nations are beams from Chriſt, as he is the Light and Word of God to the natural man, but not as he is a Redeemer, <hi>John</hi> 1. 9. and 5. 33.</item>
                  <item>That the Light within for matter and ſubſtance is the ſame with the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and was not given for righteouſneſs, nor can reveal life, <hi>Rom. 10 7, 8, 9, 10 2 Cor. 4. 6.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>That Chriſt came to deliver us from the light within, <hi>Luke</hi> 11. 34. 35, 36.</item>
                  <item>That Chriſt is no giver of Laws, <hi>Iſai. 33. 22. 1 Cor. 9. 21. Jam 4. 12. Rom 8. 2.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>That Chriſt ſet forth as the Word, the Light, the Truth, the Spirit, as a Man holy, ſpotleſs, ſeparate from ſinners, as a living example to the world, of perfect obedience to the Law
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:115288:25"/>
of the Spirit, and life of God, ſo denies and blots out the glory of his grace, as being the end of the Law, <hi>Rev. 19. 13. John 8. 12 John 14. 6. Heb. 7. 26. 1 Pet. 2. 21. Rom. 8. 2.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>That a Man may ſee himſelf dead, and buried with Chriſt, and raiſed up together with him, and not by any obedience to Chriſt within, <hi>1 Pet. 1. 2. 22.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>That the Light within is that ſpirit of this world, that hath formed all falſe reſemblances of Chriſt, <hi>Luke</hi> 11. 34, 35. 36.</item>
                  <item>That the true likeneſs and Image of Chriſt is not known to the light within, <hi>1 Cor. 12. 3.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>That the conception of Chriſt, as a Law-giver and work, is an Idol, and the root of all idolatrous Religions, <hi>James 4. 12. Iſay 33. 22.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>That the Law in the conſcience aroſe againſt Chriſt, <hi>1 Pet. 3. 21.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>That a Man is juſtified from ſin, while the Light within con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns of ſins, <hi>1 John 3. 19, 20, 21.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>That Jeſus Chriſt came forth and took the work of the Law out of the heart, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 15, 16.</item>
                  <item>That the Light within accuſing for ſin pertaineth onely to the fleſh, <hi>John</hi> 16. 8, 13.</item>
                  <item>That Chriſt comes not down into our perſons as a light accuſing for ſin, <hi>John</hi> 16. 8, 13.</item>
                  <item>That Light within which leads to know God as God, and glorifie him as God, and returns to God, obedience there to juſt and perfect, as God is juſt and perfect, this knows nothing of the Goſpel-Miniſtry, God manifeſted in fleſh, <hi>2 Cor. 4. 6.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>That this Light was not given for righteouſneſs, which will do all this before mentioned.</item>
                  <item>Theſe need no anſwering to any who have received and felt any thing of God, they can all witneſs, that not any thing of God did they ever ſee, feel, or know, but within, for it is the Spirit that ſearcheth and reveals all things, even the deep things of God: now is there any man that knows any thing as he ought to know, but by Chriſt enlightening his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding within; that work thou oppoſing ſhews thy blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:115288:25"/>
and oppoſition to Scripture, as may be ſeen.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Many more ſuch like errors haſt thou, which are directly oppoſite to the Spirit of God and plain Scripture, ſuch as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed give Chriſt a name to have lived and died in his own perſon at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> but doth wholly ſtrike at his eternal life, and the everlaſting offering, his long ſuffering, his death, and the fellowſhip of it, and his reſurrection, his enlightening, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and ſalvation in Spirit within, without which no man can be ſaved, nor know Chriſt, but as the Devil may know him; and in plain truth ſtrikes at his everlaſting Name, as he is an everlaſting King and Saviourin his people, to waſh, to order, to judge, to give laws and ſtatutes, to ſave and redeem from every particular ſin, in every one of his, from one gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to another, by his preſent in-dwelling, who is the ſame yeſterday, to day and for ever, where he is marifeſt infleſh to take away ſin.</p>
               <p>And by talking of his bloud at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> makes his bloud of none effect, as he is an everlaſting Prieſt, by an everlaſting Prieſthood, not as in one generation, but for ever, ſtands of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered up to the Father, with his bloud in the everlaſting Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant an atonement making, and beſprinkling the hearts and conſciences of every one of his by the bloud of his everla ſting Covenant, which not being done by faith within, makes that at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> of none effect as to that perſon.</p>
               <p>And this is the ſame Spirit that in the Law cryed, the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the Temple, but to withſtand him, who was the everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Temple, and ſubſtance of the viſible, which now cries, the body and bloud at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> but to withſtand the end of that blood, which is to waſh and cleanſe from all ſin, and to purge every Conſcience from dead works, without which that at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is made void, and without its effect, and as the Devil could keep then them blind in the Temple worſhip, but he in their hearts, and they doing his work, ſo doth he now by crying the death at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and keeping from the fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of it within, he keeps ſin alive, and the creature captiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted therein at his will, and makes them believe they were cleanſed before they were born, but ſtill in the ſame iniquity
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:115288:26"/>
the Jews was in (if not worſe) and cries up a great benefit they have by Chriſts coming, and that they are under grace, but ſtill in the power of Satan, and his works done in the body where Chriſt ſhould dwell; ſo that in truth this is all the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit that is found in ſuch, more than the Jews had, but a talk of Chriſt at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> as the other did of the Temple at <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> but both without that in them, which is the life of all viſibles, and inviſibles, even the in-dwelling of Chriſt to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem them from the power of ſin, and the world; but theſe cry, we are redeemed by the bloud of Chriſt before we were, though we commit ſin, that cannot hinder our redemption, we are delivered, though we be incloſed up in a body of ſin, yet are we in Chriſt at the very ſame time in the heavenly Righteouſneſs, far above all ſin (as thou ſayes) which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is no more but an imagined freedom, and a lie, and is found no more in ſubſtance, nor before God is there any differenceat all between a ſervant of ſin the Jews time, and a ſervant of ſin now, but onely that you cauſe the Name of Jeſus to be evil ſpoken on through the world, and ſin againſt his light and grace more than they did; and make the ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Chriſt at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> a cloak for the Devil to carry his works under, and bring them forth.</p>
               <p>Neither did ever any Child of light profeſs ſuch a faith (to wit) that they were waſhed and juſtified when they were not, which is a meer fixion of the brain, and no faith, but a peice of non-ſenſe, to ſay we were juſtified, ſanctified and waſhed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we were; as though that which is filthy may be made clean, by waſhing a thing that is not, and by juſtifying a thing that is not, you are juſt before God, in all manner of filthineſs, and ſo in an airy conceit of juſtifying of nought, you imagine you are ſaved.</p>
               <p>Neither did ever any of the children of light ſay, that they was juſtified before faith, as thou doſt; produce thy brother amongſt all the Saints that was of this faith, thou talks of Papiſts, and falſe Opinions; I ſay, none like this, not a Ranter in <hi>England</hi> hath a larger faith, nor hath the Devil ſuch a way in all the works to keep people out of the fear of God, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:115288:26"/>
for ſin, or being guided by the Light and Spirit of Chriſt, out of the Devils work, and ſo redeemed out of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation.</p>
               <p>Was there ever ſuch a deceit as the Devil hath blinded you withal, to live in your ſin and bondage to Satan, denying the Light of Chriſt in you, and when he lets you ſee your bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage and his enemy, and what way you ſhould eſcape the pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions of the world, and his wrath that is againſt you, by his light in your conſciences: Then you call that a ſpirit of bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, and ſay you are not under that, you are redeemed from minding any thing within in the conſcience: and thus at once make ſhipwrack of a pure conſcience, and the myſtery of faith therein, and run in hand with the Devil to believelies; That you was clean before you was born, &amp; ſhall be clean when you are dead; and your ſins now cannot change Gods purpoſe, nor make his love more or leſs to you; and ſo with a brazen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed face ſetup a way, and faith, and preach it, that though you be cloſed up in ſin, and wicked in your life, ſoul, and body, and all you are, yet you are righteous before God, and that which you now love and live in, muſt not be charged upon you.</p>
               <p>And when the enemy hath got you into this deceit, and thereby ſlain the witneſs of God in you, which ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove you of ſin, and keep you in his fear, and your hearts ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, then are you fit inſtruments for his work, to withſtand the ſpiritual appearance of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt in his Saints; and for that purpoſe hath he fill'd your hearts with lies and deceits, to caſt in the way of the truth, and upon them that profeſs it, as thou haſt done in this thy book, ſlandering us to deny the Perſon of Chriſt, for no other thing, but becauſe we witneſs the end of his appearance in perſon, which is his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dwelling for ever in our hearts by faith, there to ſit as King and Prieſt to all generations, taking dominion over whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in the heart is contrary to him, which is his Seat and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in this world, wherein alone he is known, onely in the hearts of his people; without which none knows him, nor are reconciled to God by him, and this is not to deny his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:115288:27"/>
but to exalt him as King in the heart and conſcience for ever, for he is worthy, whoſe Kindom is righteouſneſs</p>
               <p>I know what Chriſt did in his own perſon, and do own and believe it, and that righteouſneſs he therein wrought, and how therein he became the onely way to the Father, the Truth, and the Life, and the Light of all the world, ſet up for ever to lead to God, and that therein he is the firſt and the laſt, and there is none beſides him with the Father, an Advocate, Mediator, and Interceſſor, given of the Father into the world, to that end, that all men through him might be believe and be ſaved, this I own and know, and much more: But that any can be ſaved by him, without faith and obedience to him, and walking in him, who is the Way, Light and Life onely by thinking they believed what he did at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that I deny, and that faith which is without works, is no more than what the Devils hath, which will not ſave them nor any elſe; but in him is the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption not in a talk of him; and he that is in ſin is not in him; for he that abides in him ſins not; nor hath any the benefit of what he is to a believer, but as they receive his light that ſhews them ſin, and ſo turn to him by repentance, till then what he is in his own perſon, or hath done, is ſo far from ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving any, that it is their condemnation that he is come a light into the world, and they ſtill walk in darkneſs, and not in him.</p>
               <p>And alſo whatever the Scripture doth declare of him I own, and ſo do all who in the light dwell, from which the letter was given forth; and therefore be aſhamed of thy lies that thou haſt caſt upon us in this part of thy book alſo, which are not worth anſwering, being moſt of them anſwered, and denied in my anſwer to the other part of thy book, to which alſo thou haſt added in this ſuch things as never entred into our hearts to do, nor ſpeak, which thou moſt falſly accuſeſt us withal, as that we ſay:</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>That the Light which enlightens every man, accuſing of ſin, is Chriſt and God, the Eternal and Juſt One, and ſo the Redeemer and Saviour, and the all to be known and believed.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>That the returning into the Light again, Man is reſtored and redeemed as at the beginning.</hi> When we ſay, Its the Light that
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:115288:27"/>
leads to the bloud of cleanſing, &amp;c. 1 <hi>John</hi> 1. 6, 7.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>That this Light, as condemning of ſin is the bloud and death of the croſs, the reſurrection and ſecond coming of the Son of God.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>That the Law and Goſpel, Faith and Obedience, Death, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, Redemption, Juſtification and Sanctification are not things diſtinct, but one and the ſame within us.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>That we deny the Perſon of Chriſt as the object of Faith.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>That we deny Faith it ſelf as the evidence of things not ſeen.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>That we affirm, in effect that Chriſt is divided.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>That we affirm, that Paul and every Chriſtian are crucified, and made an offering for himſelf.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>That we ſay the Light in every man is Chriſt the Redeemer.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>That the Law, from which Chriſt came to deliver us, is called and worſhipped by us as the Redeemer and Spirit.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>That the Quakers ſay, that Chriſt took on him our nature, but not our judgment and ſin.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>That Chriſt died at</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>but as an example, but not as a Sacrifice.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>That he did not the work by himſelf at once, but onely ſhewed the way.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>That we reckon Chriſt to be ſuch a one as was the Prieſt and Levite that paſſed by the wounded man.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>That we deny the dead body and fleſh of Chriſt to be the onely way into the inward life.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>That nothing will ſerve us, but to tear out of your faith, and knowledge, and profeſſion, the bloud of atonement, redemption and reconciliation by that our ſacrifice once for ever.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>That we deny that Chriſt in the body of his fleſh, through that obedience to death, be crucified our old man, purged away ſin, made reconciliation for iniquity, and perfected for ever all that are ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified.</hi> Which thing we do not deny to all that are ſanctified, but to you, who are yet in your ſins, we do, elſe we ſhould lie as you do.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>That we agree with the Papiſts in this, that works or obedience to ſome Law or Rule is the way to redemption, perfection and God.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:115288:28"/>
                     <hi>That we deny the Jeſus that died, and therein by bloud and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit perfected us for ever by himself.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>That we affirm, that God requires the ſame obedience of our ſelves as he did of Chriſt, and ſo we conclude we muſt be juſtified by the works of the Law: ſlandering us that we teach Chriſt one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as an Allegory.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>That we make faith void and the bloud of Chriſt of none effect.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>And divers more deceits out of thy own blind heart haſt thou made up into lies, and laid upon us, as though we ſaid them, when they are but thy own blindneſs of heart and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful wickedneſs; in all which it is clearly ſeen, that thou doſt not mind any thing of God in thee to guide thy tongue, or to lead thee to do as thou wouldeſt be done by, And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore becauſe thou haſt rejected the light of Chriſt and ſet thy ſelf by thy lies to oppoſe it, therefore art thou given over to blindneſs of heart, and to make lies thy covering, and as thou haſt choſen them againſt the light, ſo ſhalt thou be filled therewith, and covered with thick darkneſs, ſo into thy bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els be they returned and the truth cleared.</p>
               <p>And as for thy whole work, it is judged by all who have the knowledge of the life of God, and its workings in them, and who hath a love to Righteouſneſs, ſuch as know his work, and who it is as works it, will not change that faith that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veals the workings of redemption and freedom from every particular ſin, in their meaſures daily, and peace thereby from condemnation, by the preſence of him that works all their works in them, ſuch will not change their faith for a fancy of what thou imagines was done for thee, thou knows not when where, nor doth the effects thereof appear further than a talk with all the world.</p>
               <p>Onely thy doctrine will be acceptable to ſuch as would be ſaved, but the way of God is too ſtrait, who likes not to bear the Croſs by which living Redemption is now wrought, a Redemption in a talk is very pleaſing to ſuch, that they may live with the world while they live, and be ſeparated from them when they die.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:115288:28"/>
Alſo ſuch as have got a wound from the Lord in their hearts and conſciences for their ſelfish wicked wayes, to ſuch thy ſalve of juſtification from ſin before they commit it, will ſerve to heal the heart deceitfully, as the falſe Prophets ever did, who cried peace where God cried not peace, but that peace will break out again when you ſtand in moſt need, it will onely ſerve you while you can pleaſe your ſelves in the things of this world, and forget your later end, but if ever you remember Chriſts juſtification, ſpoken on <hi>Math:</hi> 12. 36, 37. it will marr yours; to wit, that for every idle word you muſt anſwer for at the day of judgement, and then by your words you muſt be juſtified, and by your words condemned, you that live and die in your ſins will find it in vain at that day to plead your juſtification before you was born, or had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ſin, ſo to that day I leave you, who will not be recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to God, but chuſe your own deluſions.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:115288:29"/>
            <head>And from thy own words theſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Quaeries are propounded, and left with thee.</head>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>Quaer.</hi> 1. SEing thou affirms, that Chriſt hath quite taken away ſin before people are born; then, Whether doth any come into the world without ſin or no?</p>
            <p n="2">2. If Chriſt took away all ſin before you were born, as though it had never been, how is it you ſay, you expect his appearance again to ſalvation? muſt you be twice ſaved? and when there is nought to be ſaved from?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Whether he that believes that all his ſins are taken away before he be born, as though they had never been, (as thou ſayeſt) and yet commits ſin, and hath the root of it in him, doth not believe a lie, yea, or no?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Whether he that hath his ſin done away, as though it had never been, needs to repent of any thing he doth, as ſin, or grieving of the Spirit of God, yea, or no?</p>
            <p n="5">5. Whether he that believes his ſins are waſhed away be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he be born, and after he be born doth commit ſin, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he doth ſtand in need to be waſhed again? and if he be not waſhed again, whether he ſhall die in his ſins or no?</p>
            <p>ſt. Suppoſe thou that cals thy ſelf a Believer ſhould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit a ſin, as covetouſneſs, which is idolatry, or the like; if one thou cals an unbeliever do the ſame, whether is thy ſin as great as his, and ſtands need of waſhing as he, or elſe periſh with him without repentance, or what is the difference, as to the root, matter and offence?</p>
            <p n="7">7. Whether did not Chriſt waſh, ſanctifie and juſtifie all mankind in the ſame manner he did thee before thou waſt? and if not, what is the difference, and the cauſe, and the ground of it?</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:115288:29"/>
            <p n="8">8. Is there any Creature living, that if they mind the light of Chriſt, and ſo come to repentance and faith in Chriſt Jeſus, improving what power God hath given, but they ſhall be ſaved? And on the contrary, is there any, though they pretend faith, yet commit ſin, and die there in without repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and waſhing, that ſhall be ſaved? And whether the purpoſe of God doth not ſtand with the Creatures, as they own or diſown the righteouſneſs of faith in Chriſt Jeſus? can any be condemned that receives it, or can any be ſaved with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it, yea, or no?</p>
            <p>Again, ſeeing thou ſayes, <hi>page 18. That this falſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception or reſemblance of Chriſt, as a Law-giver and Worker, is an Idol, and the root of idolatrous Religions:</hi> Hence I quaerie.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whether thy Chriſt thou ſpeaks on, be the ſame with that which the Scriptures ſpeak of? If the ſame, where is thy Teſtimony from Scripture for ſuch a Chriſt as is no Law-giver? If another (as in truth it is) then why doſt thou begin thy book with a lie, calling it, <hi>A Teſtimony to the true Jeſus?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Whether doſt thou own this to be a propheſie of Chriſt, <hi>Deut.</hi> 18. 15, 16, 17, 18, 19. (which the Apoſtles applied to him, <hi>Acts</hi> 3. 22, 23) [where its ſaid, <hi>I will raiſe up to thee a Prophet from the midſt of thee, &amp;c. unto him ſhall ye hearken, according to all that thou deſiredſt of the Lord thy God in Horeb, in the day of the aſſembly, ſaying, let me not hear again the voyce of the Lord my God, neither let me ſee this great fire any more that I die not. And the Lord ſaid, they have well ſpoken, I will raiſe them up a Prophet from among their brethren like unto thee, and will put my words in his mouth, and he ſhall ſpeak unto them, all that I ſhall command him. And it ſhall come to paſs, that whoſoever will not hearken nnto my words which he ſhall ſpeak in my Name, I will require it of him.]</hi> If thou own theſe words to be ſpoken of Chriſt, whether doſt thou not ſee them to hold out him as a Law-giver to his people?
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:115288:30"/>
and ſuch a Law giver, as that whoſoever did not hearken to his words ſhould be cut off, or the Lord would require it of him. Whether doſt thou own the new Covenant, the Law to be put in the heart and writ there, inſtead of giving it forth in tables of ſtone on Mount <hi>Sinai</hi> in thunder, and lighten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and fire, which the people could not bear? And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doſt thou own Chriſt to be the Miniſter of that new Covenant or new Law promiſed, which the people were to hear, or be cut off? Or whether doſt thou own Chriſt to give the Spirit into the hearts of his people to be their Law and Teacher, to teach them all things, and to lead into all righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs? In a word, Whether doſt thou own him to give forth either Precept or Spirit, ſeeing thou denies him to be a Law-giver? For the giving forth of either makes him a Law-giver.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Whether doſt thou own theſe ſayings following to be Precepts or Laws given out by Chriſt, or diſown that Chriſt that gave them forth, namely, <hi>Math. 5. 29, 30. If thy right eye offend thee, pluck it out and caſt it from thee, &amp;c. and if thy right hand offend thee, cut it off and caſt it from thee, &amp;c,</hi> Again, <hi>I ſay unto you, ſwear not at all. I ſay unto you, that ye reſiſt not evil, but whoſoever ſhall ſmite thee on the right check, turn to him the other alſo. Lay not up for your ſelves treaſures upon earth, where moth and ruſt doth corrupt. Fear not them which kill the body, but are not able to kill the ſoul. Learn of me, for I am meek and lowly in heart:</hi> and ſuch like? Are theſe Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts or Laws given forth by Chriſt, yea, or no? ſeeing thou diſowns him as a Law-giver.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Whether doſt thou own this to be Scripture? Or this Chriſt that gave this commandement, <hi>John 13. 24. A new commandement give I unto you, That ye love one another as I have loved you, that ye alſo love one another?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Seeing thou diſowns Chriſt a Law-giver, Whether doſt thou own him to be King, and Lord, and Maſter? If ſo, Whether onely titular, or in truth and power? If in power, where lies it, if he cannot give forth a Command or Law, and ſo be a Law-giver to his people?</p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:115288:30"/>
            <p n="6">6. Whom haſt thou hitherto ſerved? and whom haſt thou hitherto obeyed? ſeeing thou owns not Chriſt to be thy Law-giver. Art thou lawleſs and diſobedient? or haſt thou thy law from thy ſelf, or from Satan, or ſome other? Whoſe Law followeſt thou, ſeeing thou owns none from Chriſt?</p>
            <p>And ſeeing thou diſowns Chriſt alſo as a Worker. <hi>Quaer.</hi> Who is it that works all our works in us, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 26. 12. and with out whom we can do nothing, <hi>John</hi> 15. 4, 5: and who was it that wrought in <hi>Paul</hi> mightily, <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 19.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
